安东尼?霍普金斯
艾玛?汤普森
詹姆斯?福克斯
克里斯托弗?里弗
告别有情天
亲爱的史蒂文斯先生
Dear Mr. Stevens
过了这么久收到我的来信  可能让你很惊讶
You will be surprised to hear from me after all this time.
自从我听闻达林顿公爵死后
You've been in my thoughts
我就一直想起你
since I heard Lord Darlington had died.
我们听说他的继承人要把达林顿府邸拍卖
We read that his heirs put Darlington Hall up for sale
因为他们一点也不想保留这房子
as they no longer wished to maintain it.
报纸上也写道  既然没有人想买这样一座大宅邸
As no one would buy such a large house
于是新继承者决定把它拆解
the new earl decided to demolish it
以5000英镑的价格卖掉
and sell the stone for 5000 pounds.
我也在每日邮报里看到一些
We also saw some rubbish in the Daily Mail
让我颇为愤慨的报道
which made my blood boil:
Traitor's  Nest要被铲平了
Traitor's nest to be pulled down.
180几尼
One hundred and eighty guineas?
180几尼  还有其他出价吗
One hundred and eighty? Have we done?
女士们  先生们  接下来是拍卖会的压轴
Ladies and gentlemen, a great highlight of the sale:
414号拍卖品
Lot 414
一幅伊丽莎白时代的肖像画
the fine Elizabethan portrait
一个高贵的绅士
A Portly Gentleman.
起价是2000几尼
I'll start the bidding at 2000 guineas.
2000几尼  谢谢出价
2000 guineas, thank you.
3000  3200
3000. 3200.
3400  3600
3400. 3600.
4000  4500
4000 guineas. Four and a half thousand.
And a half.
10000 guineas is bid.
意下如何  先生  已经11500几尼了
Against you, sir, at eleven and a half thousand guineas.
11500几尼  成交
All done at eleven and a half thousand guineas.
我十分欣慰地得知
I was very relieved to read how an American millionaire
一位叫刘易斯的美国富翁  拯救了达林顿府
named Lewis saved Darlington Hall
你就不用从那里搬走了
so you wouldn't be turned out of your home after all.
他是不是就是那个
Is it the same Congressman Lewis
1963年获得爵位的那个国会议员刘易斯
who attended His Lordship's conference in 1936?
史蒂文斯先生  我经常回忆起那些往日的美好时光
Mr. Stevens, I so often think of the good old days
那时我还是达林顿府的管家
when I was the housekeeper.
工作很辛苦
It was hard work.
我也知道  史蒂文斯先生您是一个不苟言笑的人
I know
但我依旧认为那些年是我一生中最快乐的时光
but those years with you were among the happiest of my life.
现在你肯定有一帮新的手下
You must have a completely different staff now.
那些老面孔应该都不在了
Not many of the old faces around anymore.
我一直觉得达林顿公爵雇的男仆太多  没有太大必要
There's not much need for the small army of footmen
我最近也不是很顺
My own news is not very cheerful.
距离我上次给你写信的7年间
In the 7 years since I last wrote,
我又一次离开了我的丈夫
I have again left my husband
遗憾地告诉您  我的婚姻看起来是完了
and, sad to say, my marriage seems to be over.
我现在寄宿在克利夫顿的小旅馆那里
I'm staying at a friend's boarding house in Clevedon.
我不知道未来会怎样
I don't know what my future is.
自从我女儿  凯瑟琳去年结婚之后
Since Catherine, my daughter, got married,
我的生活就变得很空洞
my life has been empty.
我眼前一片茫然  不知如何来填补我的生活
The years stretch before me and if only I knew how to fill them.
但我很想能再度工作
But I would like to be useful again.
-又烤焦了  -不好意思  先生
-Burned again? -Yes, I'm sorry, sir.
厨房里一直以来总是
The rule in the kitchen has always been
厨师专注于煮早餐  放任她的助手烤面包
cook cooks the cooked breakfast while her assistant toasts the toast.
为什么不给她添置一个面包机呢
Why don't we get her a pop-up toaster?
我们不需要这种小东西
We need not a new gadget
而是需要一套新的人事方案
but a revised staff plan, sir.
人事方案  我们有吗
A staff plan, huh? I didn't know we had one.
一套不怎么好的人事方案
A faulty one, unfortunately.
先生  最近
Sir, quite recently
您曾建议我应该休息一下  到处走走
you were kind enough to suggest that I go on a little holiday trip
对极了  好好放松一下
Absolutely. Certainly, take a break. See the world.
谢谢先生
Thank you, sir.
你上一次出门走访世界是什么时候
When did you last see the world?
请允许我这样讲
The world always used to come to this house,
在过去  整个世界都会聚集到这房子来
if I may say so.
确实可以这么说
You may say so.
那么下周我去伦敦时  你就放个假吧
Take off when I'm in London next week.
车子也借给你用
I tell you what, you take the car.
-那辆老戴姆勒  -先生  我不能接受
-Take the Daimler. -Good Lord, sir, I couldn't.
你跟那辆车是天生一对  史蒂文斯
You and that Daimler belong together.
您真是太好了  先生
That's most kind of you, I must say, sir. Most kind.
我想到西部去走走  听说那里有不错的风景
I'd meant to travel the West, where I understand we have splendid scenery.
也许我还能顺便去雇个人把眼前的人事问题解决掉
And I might incidentally be able to solve our problems while I'm there.
前任的女管家  现在暂时住在克利夫顿
A former housekeeper, at present living in Clevedon, has indicated
她有意愿回来继续工作
that she might be prepared to return to service.
是你的女朋友
What's this, your girlfriend?
还是余情未了
Or a former attachment?
不  先生
Oh, no, sir.
她是一个非常能干的女管家
No, but a very able housekeeper.
非常能干
A most able housekeeper.
我开玩笑的  史蒂文斯
I was just kidding, Stevens.
我很抱歉
Sorry.
知道我最喜欢英国报纸什么地方吗
You know what I like best about your papers?
这些讣告
These obituaries.
无论什么样的混蛋都能得到很体面的葬礼讣文
Every son of a gun gets this stately funeral oration.
-美国可没有这东西  -确实  先生
-It's not an art we have in the States. -Indeed, sir.
谢谢  史蒂文斯
Thank you, Stevens.
刘易斯先生
Mr. Lewis.
亲爱的贝恩太太
Dear Mrs. Benn
我计划于10月3日下午4点左右到达克利夫顿
I propose to reach Clevedon on October 3rd around 4 p. m.
如果您能写封信到亨格福德邮局与我联系
I'd be grateful for a line from you
我将不胜感激
to
我准备在那里稍作停留
where I'm planning to stop.
贝恩夫人  你一直有非常好的记忆力
Mrs. Benn, I always said you possess an amazing memory.
府邸的新主人确实是国会议员刘易斯
Our new employer is indeed Congressman Lewis
现在他已经从政治舞台退休了
though he's now retired from political life in the U.S.
他现正住在达林顿府  不久他的家人也会搬来
He's taken up residence at Darlington Hall, soon to be joined by his family.
我不得不说  对于这样一个大家庭
But I regret to say we are woefully understaffed
我们实在是人手不足
for a house this size.
贝恩夫人  下面这些话绝不是恭维
Mrs. Benn, will you permit me once again to sing your praises?
自从你因结婚而离开这里
Let me state that when you left to get married
没有任何一个女管家能做到你那样井井有条
no housekeeper ever reached your high standard in any department.
我还清晰记得你刚来达林顿府的时候
I well remember your arrival at Darlington Hall.
你就这么出乎意料地来了
You came somewhat unexpectedly,
甚至可以说很贸然
one might even say impulsively
那天我们都在忙于查格洛夫镇的聚会
while we were dead in the middle of the Charlgrove meet.
那天还有一件事让我记忆犹新
That day is marked in my memory in another way as well.
那是最后一次公爵像以前一样
It was the last time His Lordship
热忱欢迎他的邻居们
was happy to welcome his neighbours, as in the old days.
当然是由于已经好多年
Of course, it had been years
他们没有来硬拉他去打猎的关系
since any of them had coaxed him to hunt.
这是公爵从来都不喜欢的运动
It was never a sport His Lordship enjoyed or approved of.
早上好  埃尔
Good morning, Ayres.
公爵  很高兴见到您
My lord, nice to see you.
请用  先生
Excuse me, sir.
可能刚开始我对你有点冷淡  甚至不近人情
I fear I may have been a little unwelcoming, even a little short.
你的简历是我所见过的最优秀的
You presented the best references I've ever seen.
那也是当然的
Which proved to be well-deserved.
同时  我承认  你的年轻也让我有所顾虑
Though, I confess, I did have my doubts, on account of your youth.
绝不允许男性拜访者
No gentleman callers allowed, of course.
原谅我提到这一点  但我们以前在这方面出过事
Forgive my mentioning it, but we've had those problems before.
也是发生在宅子里
Inside the house too.
之前的女管家跟男管家助理私奔了
The previous housekeeper ran off with the under-butler.
当然  如果两个员工相爱并决定结婚
If two staff members decide to get married,
那也无可非议
one can say nothing.
但最让我恼火的情况是
What I find a major irritation
那些到处闲逛去追寻浪漫的员工
are those persons who go from post to post looking for romance.
女管家们在这方面特别容易陷进去
Housekeepers are particularly guilty here.
-当然不是特意针对你  -没关系
-No offense intended, of course. -None taken.
我知道仆人们开始互相恋爱
I know how a house is at sixes and sevens
会让家里变得乱七八糟
once the staff start marrying.
是的
Yes, indeed.
-能跟您说句话吗  先生  -当然
-Might I have a word, sir? -Of course.
老爷  关于上个月
My lord, it's regarding the under-butler
私奔的男副管家和女管家
and the housekeeper who ran off last month.
麻烦事  你处理的怎么样了
Bad business. How are you managing?
我找到了两个优秀的替代者
I've found two first-rate replacements.
肯顿小姐  有极优秀的工作经历
Miss Kenton, a young woman with excellent references.
举止得体  显得十分有管理能力
Very pleasing demeanour. Appears to be very able.
还有一个经验丰富的男管家
And a man with considerable experience.
-年纪大点  但乐意做男副管家  -姓什么
-Older and happy to be under-butler. -Name?
史蒂文斯
Stevens, sir.
-史蒂文斯   -是的  老爷
-Stevens? -Yes, sir.
-这不是你的姓吗   -他是我父亲
-That's your name. -He's my father, sir.
这样啊
Really?
再好不过了  很期待什么时候能见见他
Couldn't do better. I'd like to see him sometime.
他就在门外
He's outside the door.
好  带他进来
Good. Bring him in.
谢谢  老爷
Thank you, my lord.
父亲
Father.
史蒂文斯先生  你好
Mr. Stevens, how do you do?
-老爷  -你儿子是个得力管家
-My lord. -Very good man here, your son.
他把房子管理的很好  没了他可不行
He serves the house well. I don't know what we'd do without him.
-你为他骄傲吧  -非常  老爷
-Proud of him? -Very, my lord.
很对
Quite right too.
很高兴你能来到这里
Glad to have you with us.
谢谢  老爷
Thank you, my lord.
今天正餐是什么时候  下午2点  4点
What are we at dinner tonight? 14:00? 16:00?
中午12点  老爷
Twelve, sir.
很好
Right.
谢谢  老爷
Thank you, my lord.
这只水壶我不知道该放哪儿
This pitcher seems out of place here.
饭厅  当心别碰坏
Dining room. Well spotted.
-你好  威廉  -日安  肯顿小姐
-Hello, William, how are you? -Good day, Miss Kenton.
我想这些能为你的会客厅增添一份光彩
I thought these might brighten your parlour.
您说什么
Beg your pardon?
它们能给你带来好心情
They might cheer things up for you.
您真好心
That's very kind of you.
如果您愿意  我可以多采一些来
If you like, I could bring in some more for you.
谢谢
Thank you
但是我把这间屋子当作私人工作室
but I regard this room as my private place of work
希望尽量少摆设一些让我分心的东西
and I prefer to keep distractions to a minimum.
您怎么会认为这些花会让您分心呢
Would you call flowers a distraction, then?
我感谢您的好意  屋子还是保持原样为好
I appreciate your kindness. I prefer to keep things as they are.
既然你在这儿了  有件事我想对您说
But since you are here, there is a small matter I wanted to mention.
昨天早上我正巧从厨房经过
I happened to be walking past the kitchen yesterday morning
听到你叫某人"威廉"
and I heard you call to someone named William.
请问您是在称呼哪位
May I ask who you were addressing by that name?
我应该是在称呼您父亲
I should think I was addressing your father.
这里没有其他人叫威廉
There are no other Williams in this house.
是这样
True.
请您以后称呼我父亲"史蒂文斯先生"
May I ask you in future to address my father as Mr. Stevens?
如果是在对下属提到他时  你可以称他
If speaking of him to a third party, you may call him
史蒂文斯一世  作为与称呼我的区别
Mr. Stevens Sr. to distinguish him from myself.
我会很感激您这么做的  肯顿小姐
So I would be most grateful to you, Miss Kenton.
我不是很理解您的意思
I don't quite understand what you're getting at.
我是这里的女管家  您父亲是副男管家
I am the housekeeper in this house, and your father is the under-butler.
我习惯用下属的名字来称呼他们
I am accustomed to addressing under-servants by their Christian names.
请先停下  听我说
If you would stop to think for a moment, you'd realize
像您这样用名字直接称呼我父亲
how inappropriate it is for one such as yourself to address as William
是极为不合适的
someone such as my father.
想必您父亲一定觉得很难堪
It must have been very galling for your father to be called William
像我这样身份的人直呼其名
by one such as myself.
我想说的是  如果您仔细观察
My father is a person from whom
您将从他身上学到不少东西
if you'd observe him more, you may learn things.
我很感激您的建议  但请一定要告诉我
I'm grateful for your advice, but do tell me
我能从他那儿学到什么
what things might I learn from him?
请允许我指出一点
I might point out that you're
您还不是很熟悉一些物品的摆放位置和用途
often unsure of what goes where and which item is which.
我确信史蒂文斯一世精于他的工作职责
I'm sure Mr. Stevens Sr. is very good at his job
但我也向您保证  我也对于自己的工作十分擅长
but I can assure you that I'm very good at mine.
-当然  -谢谢
-Of course. -Thank you.
请允许我先告辞了
If you will please excuse me.
好吧
Oh, well.
向我们的厨师致意
My compliments to cook.
多么美味的脆皮
What a lovely piece of crackling.
你好像说了些有趣的话  跟大家分享一下吧
I'm sure you said something witty. Share it with the rest of us.
我说这些青豆做的很棒  我很喜欢
I said the sprouts is done the way I like them.
很干脆  没有太硬
Crisp-like, not mushy.
应该是很"松脆"  不是很"干脆"
Sprouts "are" done, not " is" done.
对吧  乔治
Isn't that right, George?
是的  史蒂文斯先生
Yes, Mr. Stevens.
抱歉纠正你的用词  因为我在你这年纪
Forgive the correction, as I would have done
十分注重养成自己的言语得当
at your age for the sake of my education.
我相信你也和其他人一样有志于升职
I'm sure even you have ambitions to rise in your profession.
是的  我也想成为一个管家  被称呼为某某先生
Oh, yes. I want to be a butler, to be called Mister
坐在自己的小客厅  有自己的壁炉
sit in my own pantry by my own fire,
嘴上叼着雪茄
smoking my cigar.
你知道要成为一个优秀的管家最重要的是什么
I wonder if you realize what it takes to be a great butler?
保持庄重  处乱不惊
Takes dignity, that's what it takes.
谢谢  史蒂文斯先生  重点是要处乱不惊
Thank you, Mr. Stevens. Dignity, that's right. Dignity.
绅士中的绅士  这本杂志上给出的定义是这样
The definition from our quarterly The Gentlemen's Gentleman:
优秀的管家必须要做到超乎想象的处乱不惊
A great butler must be possessed of dignity-
才能保住他的职位
In keeping with his position.
曾经在印度有一个英国管家
There was this English butler in India.
一天他走到饭厅里  发现有什么东西在桌子下
One day, he goes in the dining room and what's under the table?
一只老虎
A tiger.
他面不改色地走到客厅
Not turning a hair, he goes to the drawing room.
打扰您  老爷
Excuse me, my lord.
为了不打扰在场的女士  他轻声说
And whispering, so as not to upset the ladies:
餐厅里有只老虎
" I'm sorry. There appears to be a tiger in the dining room.
请允许我用枪射杀它
Perhaps His Lordship will permit use of the twelve-bores?"
他们继续用着茶  突然  三声枪响
They go on drinking their tea. And then, there's three gunshots.
他们谁也没觉得奇怪
They don't think nothing of it.
在印度  人们对什么事都习以为常
In India, they're used to anything.
当管家回来帮他们的茶续杯时
When the butler is back to refresh the teapots
他十分镇定地说道
he says, cool as a cucumber:
老爷  午餐将按时开始
" Dinner will be served at the usual time, my lord.
我也向您保证  到时餐厅里会跟往常一样
And I am pleased to say there will be no discernible traces left
不会留下任何异样的痕迹
of the recent occurrence by that time. "
这句话  "到时餐厅里会跟往常一样"
I'll repeat it. "There will be no discernible traces left
"不会留下任何异样的痕迹"
of the recent occurrence by that time. "
很精彩  史蒂文斯先生
Wonderful, Mr. Stevens.
谢谢  史蒂文斯先生
Thank you, Mr. Stevens.
精彩的故事
Wonderful story.
我们都该努力做到这一点  处乱不惊
That's the ideal that we should all aim for. Dignity.
找您的  史蒂文斯先生
For you, Mr. Stevens.
谢谢
Thank you.
是找史蒂文斯先生一世的  史蒂文斯先生
It's for Mr. Stevens Sr., Mr. Stevens.
谢谢  肯顿小姐
Thank you, Miss Kenton.
玛丽  把他的盘子放到厨师那里去保温
Put Mr. Stevens Sr. 's plate with cook to keep it warm.
是  肯顿小姐
Yes, Miss Kenton.
谢谢您  肯顿小姐
Thank you.
不用谢  史蒂文斯先生
Not at all, Mr. Stevens.
史蒂文斯先生  我看到您的扫帚在外面地上
If you're searching for your dustpan, it is out on the landing.
我的扫帚
My dustpan?
您把它放地上了
You've left it on the landing.
我没用过扫帚
I haven't used a dustpan.
是吗  那么也许是别人的
Really? It must be somebody else.
我不明白你的意思
I don't follow you.
是我弄错了  脑子不好使
My mistake, no doubt. One of many.
早上好  先生
Morning, sir.
我邀请了杜邦作为会议上法国的代表
I've invited Giscard Dupont D'Ivry as the French delegate.
他才不会来
He'll never come!
他保证说会来的
I just had word of his acceptance.
杜邦十分针对德国  他在33年日内瓦的演说
Dupont is fanatically anti-German. His speech in Geneva in 33'
让我都汗颜与法国站在同一战线
made me ashamed to be an ally of the French.
这绝不是我们英国人的做派
It's not the English way.
当然
No, it is not.
我们这次会议的目的
This is the purpose of our conference,
就是要非正式地讨论国际局势
to discuss these matters informally
绝不是那种国际化的死气沉沉的会议
far from the to-do of an international conference
而是友好地  放松地
in the friendly and relaxed
聚在某个人的家里
atmosphere of one's home.
我们可以说服法国人接受我们的观点
We may bring round the French to our point of view.
对德国人也是一样
And that of the Germans.
不过我插一句  我们怎样来联合德国人
I'm sorry to interrupt, but how can we associate with the Germans?
那可是纳粹  他们撕毁协议又践踏公约
With the Nazi Party! They have torn up and trampled every treaty
对欧洲来说是日渐增长的威胁
and are a growing threat to Europe,
更别说德国的独裁统治了
not to mention a brutal dictatorship.
年轻人  我也曾去过柏林
My dear boy, when I was in Berlin, I saw at last a happy German people
看到的是衣食无忧  热爱自己国家和元首的普通人
with jobs, bread, pride in their country and love of their leader.
那么犹太人呢
And what about the Jews?
史蒂文斯先生  老爷说要把陈列室里的中国人像
Did His Lordship wish to exchange the Chinaman in the cabinet room
放到大厅里来吗
with the one outside the door?
-中国人像   -是的
-Chinaman? -Yes.
原本在陈列室的中国人像就在门外大厅里
The Chinaman from the cabinet room is outside this door.
您自己去看一下
See for yourself.
我现在很忙
I'm busy at the moment.
就把头伸出去您亲自看一下
Just pop your head outside this door and see for yourself.
-我等会再去看  -您以为我在胡诌
-I'll look into the matter later. -You think it's a fantasy?
因为我缺乏经验所以就胡诌了吗
A fantasy on my part due to my inexperience?
我在这里的事还没忙完  肯顿小姐
I'm busy in this room, Miss Kenton.
那我等着
I shall wait.
就在门外
Outside.
看
Look!
-那不是原来在那儿的人像  -我很忙
-Is that not the wrong Chinaman? -I am very busy.
您难道没有别的事可做了吗
Have you nothing better to do than stand around?
您看一下  跟我说实话
Look at it and tell me the truth.
把声音放轻点
Keep your voice down.
其他佣人看到我们因为一个人像
What would the other servants think
而大肆争吵  会怎么想
of us shouting about a Chinaman?
那么我就请您
And I would ask you
转过身  看一看那个人像
to turn around and look at the Chinaman.
只是犯了个小错而已
It is a small mistake.
您父亲的工作量超过了他的年纪所能承受的
Your father is entrusted with more than he can cope with.
让我过去
Let me pass.
是您父亲把扫帚放在了楼梯上
Your father left the dustpan on the floor.
他忘记了磨刀具  又把人像搞错了
He left polish on the cutlery and confused the Chinaman.
在他犯下大错之前  你要认清现状
Recognize this before he commits a major error!
您不能用这种语气跟我说话
You can't talk to me like this.
恐怕我不得不这样
I'm afraid I must.
我是在给您提建议
I'm giving you serious advice.
为了他的健康  必须得给他减轻一些工作量
Your father should be relieved of a number of his duties for his own good.
不论他曾经多么能干
Whatever he once was,
他现在已经没有那份精力和体力了
he no longer has the same ability or strength.
我感谢您的建议
I thank you for your advice.
现在我要继续做我的事了
Perhaps now I can go about my business.
我从没想过要打扰您做事
I never meant to keep you from your business.
谢谢
Thank you.
我们要尽快达成一项公约  赶在
It's vital that we've agreed a common policy before the arrival of
在那个法国人来之前  他叫什么来着
your Frenchman. What's his name?
吉斯卡德  杜邦
Giscard Dupont D'Ivry.
同时我们也将迎来美国代表
We also expect the American delegate
国会议刘易斯  也会在同一天到达
Congressman Lewis, to arrive on the same day.
这个美国人是谁
Who is he, this American?
他是一个未知数
He's an unknown quantity.
一个年轻的宾夕法尼亚议员
A young congressman from Pennsylvania.
在一些国际会议上也有崭露头角
Sits on some sort of powerful Foreign Affairs Committee.
大概是某个有钱的美国佬的后裔
Heir to one of those American fortunes.
-原来是卖肉的   -卖手推车的
-Meatpacking? -Trolley cars?
还是卖干货的
Or dry goods?
干货是什么东西
What are dry goods?
反正是美国人以此赚了大钱的东西
Something that Americans make a lot of money in.
我认为刘易斯先生的财富是来源于化妆品
No, I think Mr. Lewis' fortune comes from cosmetics, actually.
是老史蒂文斯
It's old Mr. Stevens!
拿个靠垫来  还有毯子
Get a cushion, quickly. A blanket!
银器！(摔坏了)
The silver! The silver!
老爷  对不起
Oh, my lord. Sorry.
你会没事的
You'll be all right.
谢谢老爷  对不起  出了什么事
Thank you, sir. I'm sorry. What happened?
-他端着盘子  被绊倒了  -我从窗内看到了
-He tripped with the tray. -I saw it from the window.
这以前从没发生过  老爷
This has never happened before.
-我可以打电话叫医生来吗   -当然
-May I telephone the doctor? -Yes, do.
-对不起  -别担心
-I'm sorry. -Don't worry.
你父亲好些了吗
Your father feeling better?
他完全恢复了  老爷
He's made a full recovery.
很好
Good.
我们都不希望那样的事再发生  对吧
We don't wish to see anything of that sort ever happen again, do we?
我是指你父亲摔倒这事
I mean, your father collapsing.
确实是这样  老爷
Indeed not, my lord.
而且无论何时  无论何地
And it could happen anywhere.
都可能发生
At any time.
听着  第一位外国代表将在两周内到达
The first of the foreign delegates will be here in less than a fortnight.
我们都做了充分的准备  老爷
We are well prepared, my lord.
我毫不怀疑这一点
I'm sure you are.
在这里发生的事情将
What happens within this house could have
对整个欧洲的命运产生影响
considerable repercussions on the course that Europe takes.
这件事意义重大
It means a great deal.
对于我个人来讲也是十分重要
And it means a great deal to me personally.
我有个德国朋友  卡尔?汉斯
I had a German friend, Karl-Heinz Bremann.
我们在战时属于敌对的两边
We fought on opposite sides in the war.
但是我们约定  等战争结束
We always said when it was over,
可以一起坐下来好好喝一杯
we'd sit down and have a drink
像普通人一样
like gentlemen.
但是凡尔赛条约却让我无颜以对
The Versailles Treaty made a liar of me.
无颜以对  史蒂文斯
Yes, a liar, Stevens.
因为盟军制订的那些制裁条款太过猛烈
Because the terms we imposed were so harsh
以至于整个国家的经济行将崩塌
that Germany was finished.
对于战败国来说  不应该是这样的
One doesn't do that to a defeated foe.
一旦举白旗投降  就应该全部都结束
Once your man's on the canvas, it ought to be over.
我那个德国朋友  被通货膨胀给害惨了
My friend Bremann was ruined by inflation.
在战后的德国连一份工作都找不到
Couldn't get a job in postwar Germany.
于是自杀了
Killed himself.
在一节火车车厢里开枪自杀了
Shot himself in a railway carriage.
从那时候起  我便觉得有义务帮助德国并
Since then, I've felt it my duty to help Germany and to give her
给这个国家公平的对待
a fair chance.
所以这场会议非常的关键
So this conference is crucial
不能有任何的意外来打乱会议的秩序
and we can't run the risk of any accidents.
你父亲可以不用离开
There's no question of your father leaving.
你只要重新安排一下他的工作就行
You're simply being asked to reconsider his duties.
当然  老爷  我完全明白
Of course, my lord. I understand fully.
很好
Good.
那这事就交给你了  史蒂文斯
I'll leave you to think about it, then, Stevens.
谢谢  老爷
Thank you, sir.
餐厅里缺人手  需要你到备餐室帮忙
I'm short-handed in the dining room. I can use you in the servery.
-谢谢  史蒂文斯先生  -表现机灵点
-Thank you, Mr. Stevens, sir. -Smarten up. Look sharp.
早上好
Good morning.
我猜你肯定早起准备工作了
I might've known you'd be up and ready for the day.
我已经起床两个小时了
I've been up for two hours.
那样睡眠会不足
That's not much sleep.
对于我  这些时间够了
It's all the sleep I need.
我来跟你谈一谈
I've come to talk to you.
说吧  我有一上午的时间
Talk, then. I haven't got all morning.
-那我直说了  -那你就快说吧
-I'll come straight to the point. -Do, and be done with it.
你还有好些事要做
Some of us have work to be getting on with.
下周这里要举办一个很重要的国际会议
There's to be a very important conference in this house next week.
各国的政要都会来这里作客
People of great stature will be His Lordship's guests.
我们必须要做到万无一失
We must all put our best foot forward.
鉴于父亲您最近的意外
Because of Father's recent accident
建议您不用再端盘子服侍用餐了
it has been suggested that you no longer wait at table.
我每天当男仆服侍用餐
I've waited at table every day
已经做了54年了
for the last 54 years.
您以后也不用再端那些重的盘子了
It has also been decided that you should no longer carry heavy trays.
这是一张修改过的工作清单
Now, here's a revised list of your duties.
听着  我跌倒
Look, I fell
是因为地上的石块不平整
because of those paving stones.
有凸起的石块
They're crooked.
你为何不在下一个人因此摔倒前去修整一下地面
Why don't you get them put right before someone else falls?
您看一下修改过的工作内容
You will read the revised list of your duties.
去把那些石块给整平了
Get those stones put right.
你不想让那些重要人物因此摔断脖子吧
You don't want those "gentlemen of stature" breaking their necks.
当然不
No, indeed, I don't.
怎么了
What is it?
接下来您的工作需要到处走
You have what we can call a roving commission.
换种说法  就是最大限度地
In other words, you can exercise your own judgment
自由工作
within certain limits, of course.
这是你的拖把
Now, here are the mops, and  Here.
-这是我的拖把  -对  这是你的刷子
-Are these me mops? -Right. Your brushes.
这是我的刷子
And me brushes?
-这是我的拖把  -对
-And me mops. -That's right.
你想让我用它们做什么
What do you want me to do with them?
我想你知道要怎么做  父亲
I think you know what to do with them, Father.
擦灰尘和污垢
Look for dust and dirt.
如果我发现任何的灰尘和污垢
If I find any dust or dirt
我就用拖把解决掉
I go over them with this mop.
对极了
That's right.
我建议您先从
Now, I suggest you start off
这些门把手开始
with the brasses on the doors.
先那边的一扇门  然后是那边开着的那扇
There's that door there. Then the door that's open.
然后那边的门
And then there's this door here
这是你的抛光剂和除尘掸
Here's your polish. And duster.
接下来的一些日子  这里将会创造一段历史
History could well be made under this roof over the next few days.
你们中的每一个人
Each and every one of you
都该为自己在这段时间中的付出感到自豪
can be proud of the role you will play on this occasion.
想象自己身在军队的最前沿
Imagine yourself the head of a battalion
即使你只是在往水壶倒热水
even if it is only filling the hot-water bottles.
每个人的工作都有价值
Each one has his own particular duty
你们各有所长的价值
or her particular duty, as the cap fits.
给铜器抛光  把银器擦亮
Polished brass, brilliant silver,
把红木擦得像镜子一般能映出形状
mahogany shining like a mirror.
这是对这些外国来客最好的欢迎
That is the welcome we will show these foreign visitors
让他们知道  这是在英国
to let them know they are in England
在这里秩序和传统仍然是不变的主流
where order and tradition still prevail.
谢谢  布莱恩
Thank you, Brian.
老爷  那个美国人刘易斯先生到了
Mr. Lewis, the American, has arrived.
他本该明天才到  你怎么安排他的
He was expected tomorrow. What have you done with him?
已经把刘易斯先生带到楼上房间了
Mr. Lewis has been shown upstairs.
我的教子  卡迪纳尔  最近告诉我要结婚了
My godson, Cardinal, will shortly become engaged to be married.
真好  老爷  恭喜您
Indeed, sir. I offer my congratulations.
谢谢  史蒂文斯
Thank you, Stevens.
我自认对这个孩子责任很重
I feel very responsible for the boy.
你知道他父亲是我最好的朋友  让我当这孩子的教父
He is my godson, and his father was my closest friend, as you know.
现在他去世了
And now that he's gone, well
我感觉自己就像是他父亲一样
I feel in place of a father to him.
我任命他在会议上作我的秘书
I've appointed him as my secretary at the conference.
他很高兴地帮助我做准备
He's been jolly thorough in helping me to prepare.
我也知道拜托你的这件事  有点不合规矩
I realize this is a somewhat irregular thing to ask you to do.
我很高兴能帮上您的忙
I'd be glad to be of any assistance.
我很不好意思说起这事
I'm sorry to bring this up
但是这事一直萦绕在我心头
but I just can't see how on earth to make it go away.
你对大自然基本原理知识很熟悉  对吧
You are familiar with the facts of life?
-什么   -大自然基本原理
-My lord? -The facts of life.
鸟儿啊  蜜蜂啊等等  你很熟悉  对吧
Birds, bees. You are familiar, aren't you?
我不太理解老爷您的意思
I'm afraid I don't quite follow you.
那我说的直白一点
Let me put my cards on the table.
最近我忙于准备这次会议  当然你也很忙
I'm so busy with this conference. Of course, you are too
但是必须得有人教教他
but someone has to tell him.
某种程度上  由你去说可能更轻松
In a way, it would be easier for you.
不那么尴尬
Less awkward.
我一直羞于跟他开口说这事
I'd find the task rather daunting, I'm afraid.
可能到他结婚那天都不会说出口
I might not get to it before Reginald's wedding day.
当然这远超出了你的职责范围
Of course, this goes far beyond the call of duty.
我会尽全力的  老爷
I shall do my best.
谢谢你帮我  让我放心许多
I'd be grateful if you'd try. It'd be a lot off my mind.
这事说的时候没必要手舞足蹈
There's no need to make a song and dance of it.
就把该怎么做说出来就好
Just convey the facts.
吓死我了  史蒂文斯
God! Stevens!
抱歉  太抱歉了  先生
Sorry. Most sorry, sir
我有些重要的事向您转达
but I do have something to convey to you rather urgently.
可以的话  我就直说了
If I may, I'll come to the point.
不知你注意到了今天早晨池塘边的鸭子和鹅了吗
Perhaps you noticed this morning the ducks and the geese by the pond?
鸭子和鹅  我没怎么注意到
Ducks and geese? I don't think so.
或者鸟儿  花朵
Well, perhaps the birds and the flowers, then
或是灌木  蜜蜂
or the shrubs, the bees
我一个蜜蜂也没看到
I've not seen any bees.
现在不是最好的季节说这些
It's not the best time to see them.
什么  蜜蜂
What, the bees?
我想说的是  随着春天的到来
What I'm saying is that, with the arrival of spring
我们将会看到周围的环境会产生
we shall see a most remarkable and profound change
显著的巨大变化
in the surroundings.
你说的对  现在这庭院确实没什么风景可看
I'm sure that's right. I'm sure the grounds are not at their best now.
不过我不是在欣赏这庭院的自然风光
I wasn't paying attention to the glories of nature
因为我是在担心
because it's worrying
那个杜邦来的时候脸色很差  这是谁也不想的
Dupont D'Ivry has arrived in a foul mood, the last thing anyone wants.
杜邦先生已经来了
M. Dupont D'Ivry has arrived?
半小时前  脸色很差
Half an hour ago, in a foul mood.
这样的话  不好意思  我最好先去看看
In that case, excuse me. I'd better go and attend to him.
很高兴跟你谈话
Right you are. Kind of you to talk to me.
不客气  先生  我还有一些话想传达给你
Not at all. I've one or two words more to convey on the topic of
关于如您说所的
as you put it most admirably
大自然的风光
the glories of nature.
但似乎得另找时间了
But it must wait for another occasion.
我很期待下次谈话  但我更喜欢谈论钓鱼
I'll look forward to it. But I'm more of a fish man.
-鱼   -我非常喜欢钓鱼
-Fish? -I know all about fish.
淡水鱼和海水鱼
Freshwater and salt.
所有的生物对于我们的话题都是有意义的
All living creatures would be relevant to our discussion.
抱歉  我不知道杜邦先生已经到了
Excuse me. I had no idea that Monsieur Dupont D'Ivry had arrived.
谢谢
Thank you.
有什么可以效劳的  先生
May I be of assistance, sir?
太好了  是管家
Oh, the butler.
我的脚发炎了  请给我一盆热水和盐
I have sore feet, so I need a basin with warm water and salts, please.
我会去找女管家安排的  先生
I'll arrange that with the housekeeper, sir.
热水和盐  尽快
Warm water and salts as soon as possible.
你好  我也会说英语
How do you do? But I speak English.
好极了  我很幸运
Good. That's lucky for me.
我是杰克?刘易斯  美国的代表
I'm Jack Lewis, the U.S. delegate.
我们能私下谈谈吗
Could we speak privately soon?
当然
Yes, of course.
但是因为他们强迫我去观光弄的我脚底全是水泡
But I have blisters due to some sightseeing they made me do in London.
知道吗  我之前早就看过伦敦塔了
I had already seen the Tower of London.
我发现事情并没有如我预料的
I've discovered that things are not moving
向您所希望的方向发展
in a direction that I think you would approve of.
重整德国军备需要被大家所认可
German rearmament is a fact to be accepted.
我们都希望看到的是一个自由和平等的德国
It's in our own interest to have a free and equal Germany.
而不是一个被
Not a prostrate nation
16年前的不平等条约压垮的德国
upon whom an unfair peace treaty was imposed 16 years ago.
那些像我一样曾去过德国的在座各位
Those who've been in Germany
应该感到激动  因为我们看到了德国重生的希望
can only thrill, as I have, to the signs of rebirth.
为了帮助德国恢复国内经济
-to assist Germany in her virile struggle for economic recovery
包括提供日常补给和相当的军备
including support for her fair demand for equality of armaments
以及对德国青年提供全球性的兵役政策
and universal military service for German youth.
如果我们  在战后的欧洲
If we, in postwar Europe
再给我弄一盆水泡脚
I need more water. I need another basin to bathe my feet.
跟我来  先生
Follow me, sir.
-我们必须得谈谈  -这边请  先生
-We have to talk. -This way, sir.
我的朋友  我现在很痛
My friend, I am in agony.
鞋子太紧了  都怪我自己
Too tight shoes. I blame myself.
虚荣心
Vanity.
我们必须得做些什么来制约德国
We must do some fast maneuvering to restrain the Germans.
请这边请  先生们
Please come this way, gentlemen.
管家  你可以帮我把鞋子脱下吗
Butler, please, could you help me with my feet-shoe?
当然
-Yes, of course. -Take it off.
你也听到他们说的关于等量的军备和军事设施
What they said about equality of arms for Germany, military service-
-抱歉  先生  -我去去就来
-Sorry, sir. -I'll manage.
什么事
What?
您父亲病了  先生
Your father's been taken ill, sir.
-他在哪里   -在中式卧室门外
-Where? -Outside the Chinese bedroom, sir.
德国跟我们一样也在寻求和平
Germany wants peace as much as we do. She needs peace.
让我来帮你
Here, let me help you with that.
谢谢
Thank you.
谢谢  查尔斯
Thank you, Charles.
去准备一盆热水和盐
Take a basin of hot water and salts
给台球室里的杜邦先生送去  清楚了没
to Mr. D'Ivry in the billiards room. Is that understood?
-是的  史蒂文斯先生  -很好  去吧
-Yes, Mr. Stevens. -Good. Do it.
父亲
Father?
我比你更有时间来照看你父亲
I have more time than you to look after him.
我已经叫了医生
I've called the doctor.
谢谢  肯顿小姐
Thank you, Miss Kenton.
恐怕你父亲不太好
Your father's not so good, I'm afraid.
如果病情恶化  请通知我
If he deteriorates, call me, will you?
他多大了  70还是72
How old is he? 70, 72?
-75  -我明白了
-75, sir. -I see.
-病情恶化就通知我  -我会的  谢谢医生
-If he deteriorates, let me know. -I will, sir. Thank you, doctor.
稳当一点  别太快
More haste, less speed.
缺了什么东西
There's something missing.
什么东西
What is it?
-佐料架上的调羹  生生  -很好
-The spoon from the cruet set, sir. -Good.
看的很仔细
Well observed.
不要去碰杯子的杯沿
Now, never touch the lip of the glass.
很好
Good.
先放杯子  然后
Glass first, and then
楼下一切都好吗
Is everything in hand downstairs?
我们在准备会议期间的最后一顿晚餐
We're preparing the last dinner of the conference.
你可以想象到厨房手忙脚乱的样子
You can imagine the kitchen.
但是一切都在掌握中吗
But is everything in hand?
是的  情况良好
Yes, I think we're up to scratch.
你觉得好些了吗
Are you feeling any better?
有些事我要告诉你
There's something I have to tell you.
我有很多事要忙  明早再说吧
I have so much to do. Why don't we talk in the morning?
吉姆
Jim
我不爱你的母亲
I fell out of love with your mother.
我曾经爱过她
I loved her once.
当我不再爱她的时候  发现
The love went out of me when I found her carrying on.
她怀孕了
A good son.
但是我以你为傲
Proud of you.
我希望自己是个好父亲
I hope I've been a good father.
我尽力了
I tried me best.
你现在最好下去了
You better get down there
否则他们会乱成一锅粥的
or heaven only knows what they'll be up to.
去吧
Go on.
Go on!
我早上再来看你
We'll talk in the morning.
在我们会议的最后一天
On the last day of our conference
请允许我表达诚挚的谢意
permit me to say how impressed I have been
感谢在座各位所表现出的友善
with the spirit of goodwill that has prevailed.
同时也是也是对德国的友善
Goodwill for Germany.
让我感动得几乎流泪的是
And with tears in my eyes
我看到了各位都公认了
I see that everyone here has recognized
我们德国再一次屹立于强国之林
our right to be, once again, a strong nation.
我从心底里想对大家说
With my hand on my heart, I declare
德国需要和平
that Germany needs peace
渴望和平
and desires only peace.
与英国的和平
Peace with England
还有与法国的和平
and peace with France.
非常感谢
Thank you very much.
我也同样被感动了
I, too, have been impressed
是的  深深地被感动了
yes, deeply impressed
被会议上这种渴望和平的真诚的心所打动
by the genuine desire for peace manifested at this conference.
不像我们的美国同盟
Unlike our American colleague
我们欧洲人深知战争的恐怖
we in Europe know the horrors of war.
不论我们是法国人  英国人  意大利人或是德国人
And whether we are French or English or Italian or German
我们共同的愿望都是不想再次经历战争的伤痛
our one desire is to never have to experience them again.
确实是这样
Indeed.
让我印象深刻  或者说是被感动的是
Impressed, or I may say touched
大家的表现出的善意和友谊
by the words of goodwill and friendship I have heard
我向大家承诺  我会尽我最大的努力
I promise you that I shall do my utmost
来转变我国对德国的政策
to change my country's policy
虽然她曾是一个战败国
towards that nation which was once our foe
但是现在  我敢于说
but is now, I may venture to say
她是我们的朋友
our friend.
女士们先生们
Ladies and gentlemen
美国跟各位一样也不想要战争
the United States doesn't want war any more than you do.
但是另一方面  我们也不想用任何的代价来换取和平
On the other hand, neither do we want peace at any price
因为有些所谓的代价
because some prices, you may find
无比巨大
are too outrageously high to pay.
但是先不说这些  不久就知道了
But let's not get into that now. We may have to soon enough.
现在  让我们举起酒杯敬达林顿公爵
For the moment, let us raise our glasses to Lord Darlington
感谢他的热情好客
in gratitude for his magnificent hospitality.
达林顿公爵是一个老派的英国绅士
Lord Darlington is a classic English gentleman of the old school.
体面  受人尊敬  非常好心
Decent and honorable and well-meaning.
在座各位也都是体面  受尊敬  好心的绅士
So are all of you. All decent, honorable and well-meaning gentlemen.
非常荣幸能在这里遇到各位
It's a pleasure and a privilege to visit with you here.
但是
But
很抱歉这么说
now, excuse me, I must say this
你们都是业余的
you are, all of you, amateurs.
国际政治事务不该由你们这样的绅士来管理
And international affairs should never be run by gentlemen amateurs.
你们一点也不知道这个世界正在变成什么样
Do you have any idea of what sort of a place the world is becoming?
用你们高尚的作派来管理的世界已经不复存在了
The days when you could act out of noble instincts are over.
欧洲现在是权利政治的舞台  是现实的政治
Europe has become the arena of Realpolitik, the politics of reality.
不管你喜不喜欢  是真正的政治
If you like, real politics.
你们要讨论的不是像理想化的政治
What you need is not gentlemen politicians,
而是现实世界中的政治
but real ones.
你们需要专家来出谋划策  否则你们只会引致灾难
You need professionals, or you're headed for disaster.
绅士们  请举杯
So I propose a toast, gentlemen
向我们的专家致敬
to the professionals.
我不希望大家在相聚的最后一晚
Well, I've no wish to enter into a quarrel
陷入争论之中
on our last evening together.
但是让我说一句  你所描述的业余政治家
But let me say this. What you describe as amateurism
是我们在场的所有人都引以为傲的
is what I think most of us here still prefer to call honour.
肯顿小姐想对你说句话  关于您的父亲
Miss Kenton would like to see you concerning your father.
我猜您的专业  更意味着贪婪和权利
I suggest that your professionalism means greed and power
而不是这个世界所需要的正义和公平
rather than to see justice and goodness prevail in the world.
我毫不保留地告诉各位
I've never concealed from myself that what we were asking of Germany
这是我们国家的传统  谢谢
is a complete break from the tradition of this country. Thank you.
史蒂文斯先生  我很抱歉
Mr. Stevens, I'm very sorry.
您父亲几分钟前过世了
Your father passed away four minutes ago.
我明白了
Oh, I see.
我很抱歉
I'm so very sorry.
我希望能说些什么来安慰您
I wish there was something I could say.
您能上楼去看看他吗
Will you come up and see him?
我现在很忙  也许过一会能去看看
Well, I'm very busy at the moment. In a little while, perhaps.
这样的话  请允许我合上他的双眼
In that case, will you permit me to close his eyes?
实在感激不尽  谢谢
I would be most grateful. Thank you.
我父亲肯定希望我把工作做好  我不能让他失望
My father would wish me to carry on. I can't let him down.
是的  当然
No. Of course.
我很想继续那次的谈话
I'd really like to continue our little chat sometime.
关于大自然
About nature.
你是对的  我应该在万物复苏的时候回来看看
You're right. I should come back when everything's burgeoning.
是的  先生
Yes, sir. Indeed.
我之前说过  我最大的兴趣是钓鱼
As I said before, my main interest has always been in fish.
我小时候在鱼缸里养了一条热带鱼
When I was small, I kept tropical fish in a tank.
我非常狂热地爱好它们
I harboured quite a passion for them.
再给我倒一点酒吧
I'll have another drop of that, if you don't mind.
你还好吧
You all right?
我非常好
I'm perfectly all right.
没有觉得不舒服吗
Not feeling unwell?
没有  先生  只是有点累了
No, sir. A little tired, perhaps.
太美妙了
Wonderful!
您带来的德国音乐真是太美妙了
What a beautiful example of German culture you've brought to this house.
您唱的很好
Very nice.
但愿我没有让您难堪
I hope there's no hard feelings.
我亲爱的伙伴
Oh, my dear good chap.
真想跟你好好地干一架
I like a good, clean fight.
打人的和被打的都能乐呵呵的
Giving as good as one gets, what?
我十分尊崇英国这个国家  我非常热爱这里
I have the greatest respect for the English. I love it here.
我小时候跟家里人来过这儿  所以感觉像在家里一样
My family brought us here as kids, so I feel at home.
不管怎样  谢谢
Anyway, thank you.
失陪
Excuse me.
你没事吧
You all right?
非常好  老爷
Yes, perfect, my lord.
你着凉了还是怎么了
You coming down with a cold or something?
只是一天下来比较累
It's been a long day.
对你我来说都是累人的一天
It's been a hard day for both of us.
你做的很好
Well done.
请节哀
My condolences.
一次严重的中风  他没有遭受太多的痛苦
It was a stroke. A severe stroke. He wouldn't have suffered much pain.
谢谢您告知我
Thank you for telling me.
有个外国先生正好身体不适
There's a distinguished foreign gentleman in the billiard room
需要您去看一下
in need of attention.
很紧急吗
Urgent?
他的脚
His feet.
脚
Feet?
-我带您去见他  -但愿是很紧急
-I'll take you to him. -If it's urgent.
非常紧急  这位先生处于疼痛之中
It is urgent. The gentleman is in pain.
请节哀
My condolences.
谢谢  肯顿小姐  您真是非常好心
Thank you. That is most kind of you.
下午好
Good afternoon.
我叫史蒂文斯  我来取我的信
My name is Stevens. I'm hoping there's a letter for me.
-我帮您找找  -詹姆斯?史蒂文斯
-I'll just check for you, sir. -James Stevens.
-我还想要两个苹果  -给您  史蒂文斯先生
-I'd like two apples, please. -There you are, Mr. Stevens.
您是在旅游吗
You are touring in these parts?
我正在去克利夫顿的路上
I'm on my way to Clevedon.
-多少钱   -三便士
-How much is that? -That'll be threepence, please.
您是哪里来的
And you'd be coming from ?
-牛津郡  -靠近什么地方
-Oxfordshire. -Whereabouts?
什么   -靠近牛津郡的什么地方
-Sorry? -Whereabouts in Oxfordshire?
达林顿
Darlington.
好像有点耳熟  是不是有个达林顿公爵
That rings a bell. Wasn't there a Lord Darlington? Some sort
是个纳粹  把英国带进了二战的
of Nazi, got us in the war?
我是那里的管家  我的雇主是
I'm the butler there, and my employer
刘易斯先生  一位美国绅士
is Mr. Lewis, an American gentleman.
我对前一任屋主不熟
I didn't know the former owner.
您的找零
Your change.
我在海景饭店订了位子  就在码头对面
I should be glad to meet you at the Sea View Hotel, opposite the pier.
我们真是有太多要谈论了  我也有很多的问题
We'll have such a lot to talk about, and I'll have many questions.
除了您之外  我跟达林顿府上的朋友都失去了联系
Ex cept for you, I've lost touch with all our friends at Darlington Hall.
但这是毫无疑问的
But that's no wonder.
过了这么多年  发生了这么多事
It was long ago and a lot has happened in between.
怎么可能跟所有人都保持联系呢
Who could keep track of all the people His Lordship once employed?
老爷您找我
My lord, you rang?
年轻的德国女士到了吗
Have the young German ladies arrived?
是的  她们在外面
They're outside.
我想跟她们问个好  练练我的德语
I'd like to say hello to them, practise my German.
-她们的英语也说的很好  -很好  叫她们进来
-They do speak excellent English. -Good. Well, ask them to come in.
这是艾尔莎  这是厄尔玛
This is Elsa and this is Irma.
我在询问她们的旅途是否顺利
I'm asking about their journey.
路途很长  老爷
It was long, my lord.
我问她们是否喜欢这里的天气
I asked if they like the weather.
我们很感激您  能让我们来这里
We are grateful to you, my lord, for letting us come here.
我们的父母非常感激您
Our parents are very grateful.
不用客气  肯顿小姐会照顾好你们的
Not at all. Miss Kenton will look after you.
-对吧  -当然  老爷
-Won't you? -Indeed, my lord.
欢迎来到达林顿府
Welcome to Darlington Hall.
谢谢  老爷
-Thank you, my lord. -Thank you, my lord.
-还有别的事吗   -没了
Will there be anything else?
杰弗瑞先生
Sir Geoffrey.
很高兴见到您
Good to see you.
您好
How do you do?
请进
Well, come in.
-班恩先生  -史蒂文斯先生
-Mr. Benn. -Mr. Stevens.
先生们  在这里等一会
Gentlemen, if you'd like to wait here for a while.
您不是在史丹顿府吗
Aren't you still at Stanton Lacey?
我现在是杰弗瑞爵士的管家
I'm with Sir Geoffrey now.
-您一点也没变  -您上去吧
-You haven't changed one bit. -I'll let you get on.
-有机会再聊  -期待如此
-Perhaps we'll meet later. -I hope so.
先生们  你们谈论着犹太人  吉普赛人  黑人等等
But, gentlemen, you speak of Jews and Gypsies, Negroes and so forth.
但是你们也该看到法西斯的种族法律
But one has to regard the racial laws of the Fascists
也是一种公共卫生措施  在我看来
as a sanitary measure, much overdue, in my opinion.
想象如果要在这个国家推行这样的法令
Imagine trying to enforce such a rule in this country-
没有一套刑罚体系是不可能的
You cannot run a country without a penal system.
在这里我们称之为监狱
Here we call them prisons.
那里他们称之为集中营
There, they call them concentration camps.
史蒂文斯  这汤里有什么肉吗
Is there any meat of any kind in this soup?
这是蘑菇汤料  先生
I think it's mushroom stock, sir.
蘑菇  洋葱以及芹菜  完全没有肉
Mushroom ends and skins, onion and celery. No meat at all.
煮的时候加了点雪利酒
Cold water, and then cook adds sherry.
我听说您的选区里有工党派人士
I hear you have a Labour fellow from your constituency.
但是在德国  他们已经摆脱了工会的束缚
Over there, they've got rid of all that trade union rubbish.
没有一个工人会在德国搞罢工
Believe me, no workers strike in Germany.
每个人都十分遵守秩序
And everyone's kept in line.
难怪我们的国家在走下破路
No wonder this country is going down the drain.
是从内部蔓延出来的问题
It is internally diseased.
面包块里有黄油  你知道吗
I think there may be butter in the croutons. Do you know?
恐怕是的
I'm afraid there may be.
你这里还蛮舒适的
You've made a cozy little nest here.
在我看来  你是个十分心满意足的人
Seems to me you must be a well-contented man.
在我看来  贝恩先生
In my philosophy, Mr. Benn
人不能自诩心满意足
a man cannot call himself well-contented
直到他尽自己所能
until he has done all he can
为雇主做到应尽之事
to be of service to his employer.
当然  这要基于这个雇主
This assumes that one's employer
不仅在地位和财富上更优越
is a superior person not only in rank or wealth
在道德层面也要有高的品格
but in moral stature.
那您怎么看  楼上那帮"品格高尚之人"
And in your opinion, what's going on up there has "moral stature"?
我希望自己也能像您那样确定
I wish I could be sure.
但我不是
But I'm not.
我听闻一些可疑的事情  非常可疑
I've heard some very fishy things. Very fishy.
我什么都没听闻
I hear nothing.
听
Listen.
歌声多么动人啊
That's so touching, isn't it?
听那些先生们的谈话会让我工作分心
To listen to the gentlemen would distract me from my work.
这是新鲜的苏打水
It's fresh soda.
跟我们一起喝一杯吧
Would you be joining us?
多谢好意  但是我明天要早起
Thank you, but it's very late and I have an early start.
晚安
Good night.
-晚安  史蒂文斯先生  -晚安  肯顿小姐
-Good night, Mr. Stevens. -Good night, Miss Kenton.
漂亮的女人
Good-looking woman.
自从她离开史丹顿府  一切都不一样了
It was never the same after she left Stanton Lacey.
六个月后我也离开了那里
I handed in my own notice six months later.
若没有了她  我会不知所措
I'd be lost without her.
在这样一座影响整个世界的大房子里
A first-rate housekeeper is essential in a house like this
一个能干的女管家非常重要
where great affairs are decided between these walls.
-早上好  -老爷
-Good morning. -My lord.
我们对待犹太人并没有什么不公
"We do the Jews no injustice when we say that the revelation of Christ
犹大背叛基督既让人不能理解也招致痛恨
is something incomprehensible and hateful to them.
尽管他只是站在人群中的一个人
Though He apparently sprang from their midst
但是他象征着他们的整个族群
He embodies the negation of their whole nature.
犹太人对此比我们更敏感
The Jews are far more sensitive about this than we are.
这种障碍使得欧洲人与犹太人区别开来
This demonstration of the cleft that separates us Europeans from the Jew
并不是为了让种族主义
is not given in order to let religious prejudice
往极端方向发展
with its dangerous bias, settle the matter
而是基于这两个种族观念和本质的不同
but because the perception of two fundamentally different natures
所揭示出来的现实的鸿沟
reveals a real gulf. "
我们的仆人中有两个难民吧
We have some refugee girls on the staff now, I believe.
是的
We do.
两个女仆  艾尔莎和厄尔玛
Two housemaids, Elsa and Irma.
恐怕你得把她们送走
You'll have to let them go, I'm afraid.
让他们走吗  老爷
Let them go, my lord?
虽然很遗憾  但也是没办法的事
It's regrettable, but we have no choice.
你必须得顺应大环境
You must see the whole thing in context.
我得为我的宾客们考虑
I have the well-being of my guests to consider.
请允许我说一句
May I say
她们工作的非常好
they work extremely well.
她们很聪明  有礼貌又爱干净
They're intelligent, polite and very clean.
很抱歉  但我已经仔细考虑过了
I'm sorry, but I've looked into this matter very carefully.
我可不想冒这个险
There are larger issues at stake.
我很抱歉  就这么决定了
I'm sorry, but there it is.
她们是犹太人
They're Jews.
是  老爷
Yes, my lord.
我很惊讶你竟然站在这儿
I'm amazed you can stand there as if
像个没事人似的  难以置信
you were discussing orders for the larder. I can't believe it!
艾尔莎和厄尔玛被解雇  就因为她们是犹太人
Elsa and Irma are to be dismissed because they're Jewish?
老爷已经决定了  我和你都无权干涉
His Lordship has decided. There's nothing for you and I to discuss.
她们没有工作的话  会被送回德国的
Without work, they could be sent back to Germany.
我也无能为力
It is out of our hands.
如果明天您解雇这两个女孩  您就罪过了
I tell you, if you dismiss my girls tomorrow, it will be wrong!
罪过  就像杀人放火一样的罪过
A sin, as any sin ever was one!
这世界上有许多我和你不能理解的事
There are many things you and I don't understand in this world.
但是老爷懂的多  也权衡过利弊
His Lordship understands fully and has studied the larger issues at stake
关于
concerning, say
犹太种族的本质
the nature of Jewry.
我警告您
I warn you
如果她们被解雇
if those girls go
我也辞职不干了
I shall leave this house.
请别这样
Please.
这封推荐信  我不得不说
These references, I have to tell you
是有所保留的
are quite reserved.
你为什么离开上一个雇主
Why did you leave your last employment?
-因为他们不要我了  -为什么
-They didn't want me anymore. -Why not?
我不知道
I don't know.
他们就是不要我了
They just didn't want me anymore.
他们说她工作不错
They say she works well.
请到外面稍等一会
Would you please wait outside?
-她不合适  -没关系  留下她
-She's unsuitable. -Not at all. I want her.
-我会监督她的  -可她不合适
-She'll be under my supervision. -She's not suitable.
她会做好的  我向您保证
She'll do well. I'll see to it.
好吧  那么责任就落在您肩上了
Well, then, it is entirely your responsibility.
您不是因为那两个德国女孩要辞职吗
Weren't you leaving because of the German girls?
我不走了
I'm not leaving.
我没地方可去  我没有家
I've nowhere to go. I have no family.
我是一个懦夫
I'm a coward.
是的  我是一个懦夫
Yes. I am a coward.
我害怕离开  这是事实
I'm frightened of leaving, and that's the truth.
我所看到的外面的世界充满了孤独感  这让我害怕
All I see out in the world is loneliness, and it frightens me.
我的做人原则也被压了下去
That's all my high principles are worth.
我非常地惭愧
I'm ashamed of myself.
您是这个庄园不可或缺的
You mean a great deal to this house.
您对这个庄园非常重要
You're extremely important to this house.
是吗
Am I?
现在  回到正事上
Now, look here
如果您对这个应聘者十分有信心  那么就叫她进来
if you're really sure about this young woman, call her back in.
豪尔小姐  我们希望您下周开始工作
Miss Hull, we would like you to start next week.
你就跟着肯顿小姐  她会跟你解释这里的规矩
You're responsible to Miss Kenton. She'll explain the house rules.
第一条  不能有男性来访者  以及其他的
Number one: no gentlemen callers, or other such.
-是  先生  -很好
-Yes, sir. -Good.
-欢迎来这  -谢谢  先生
-Welcome. -Thank you, sir.
很好  我带你去你的房间
Well done. I'll show you to your room.
我都忘了老戴姆勒有多么耗油了
I'd forgotten how much petrol the Daimler uses.
我敢说  这辆车绝对不适合外出旅游
It's an impractical motor to be going about the country, Mister
我是哈里?史密斯  愿您在这里过得愉快
Smith. Harry Smith. It's a privilege to have you here in Moscombe.
-很荣幸在这里见到您  -为健康干杯
-It's a privilege to be here. -Your health, sir.
卡莱尔先生经常在这时会过来  他会很高兴见到您
Dr. Carlisle usually drops in around now. He'd enjoy meeting you.
他像您一样是个绅士
He's a gentleman like yourself.
我不知道你们所说的绅士是什么样
I don't know what you call a gentleman.
这个国家的所有男人都可以是绅士
It's a name every man in this country has a right to.
这就是哈里?史密斯  他的老掉牙的人生哲学
There's Harry Smith now, giving you an earful of his philosophy.
我们英国人
We English
擅长于表达自己的自由观点  所以形成了议会制度
have the advantage and privilege of expressing our opinions
这就是跟希特勒打仗的原因
and voting for Parliament. That's what we fought Hitler for.
您的工作跟政治沾边吗
Have you had much to do with politics yourself?
不是很多  特别是这两年
Not directly as such, no, particularly in these days.
1930年初以及战前  接触的较多
Perhaps more so in the early 1930s and just before the war.
我大多关注于国际性的事件
My concern was more international affairs.
还有外交政策之类的
Or foreign policy, so to speak.
当然我也不是那种高层人物
Not that I ever held high office, mind you.
我所接触的事情都是一些非官方的事件
No, any influence I exerted was in an unofficial capacity.
请问  先生
Excuse me, sir.
您见过丘吉尔先生吗
Have you ever met Mr. Churchill?
他偶尔会到庄园来  那是在1930年代
He came to the house occasionally. Again, in the early 1930s.
他就是个残暴的战争狂
He was a bloody warmonger!
拜托  哈里  没有他我们赢不了战争
Honestly, Harry! We wouldn't have won the war without him.
不是说他打德国人
Not content to fight Germans,
而是他竟然派装甲部队去镇压煤矿工人
he sent troops in against the miners.
他确实在战争中表现出色  但他之后就该退休了
He did well in the war, but he should've stepped down.
那么艾登首相呢
And Mr. Eden?
他把苏伊士运河的控制权弄没了
He made a right bugger of Suez!
我见过艾登先生几次
Yes, I met Mr. Eden. Yes, occasionally.
您好  我是理查德?卡莱尔
How do you do? Richard Carlisle.
您的车够倒霉的  但是很高兴见到您
Rotten luck about your car, but nice to have you.
大家都很友好
Everyone has been most kind.
这位先生在叙述一些国际性事件
He says he knows foreign affairs.
是真的吗
Is that so, indeed?
都是一些非正式的事件
In an unofficial capacity.
-他见过丘吉尔首相  -还有艾登首相
-He knows Mr. Churchill. -And Mr. Eden.
真的吗
Really?
是的  这是我的荣幸能够遇到
Yes, well, it was my good fortune to have consorted
这些影响世界历史的人物
with many men of influence from Europe and from America.
泰勒先生
Mr. Taylor
我想去休息了  这一天下来实在很疲惫
I really feel I ought to retire now because I'm feeling rather tired.
这也难怪  先是汽油用完了
No wonder, sir. Running out of petrol
然后还不断地听史密斯说他的政治观点
then having to hear Smith's political opinions.
请走这边  先生
Just step this way, sir.
明天早上我也要去史丹布瑞  也许可以载您一程
I'm going to Stanbury in the morning. I'll give you a lift
路上还可以给您的车加一罐汽油
and we could pick up a can of petrol on the way.
这样会给您带来不便
I'd hate to inconvenience you.
没关系  7点30分可以吗
Not at all. Would 7:30 suit you?
您会喜欢跟卡莱尔先生交谈  请当心楼梯
You'll enjoy talking to Dr. Carlisle. Watch this step.
请原谅哈里?史密斯
Excuse Harry Smith.
他一直这样说着他的政治观点  并不是说他不对
He will go on about his politics. I don't mean he's not right.
跟希特勒打仗是为了获得民主
Democracy is why we fought Hitler,
我们也牺牲了很多年轻人
and we lost a few lads in this village
包括我的儿子
including our son here.
在敦克尔克(阵亡)
Dunkirk.
我去给您找条毯子
I'll get you a blanket.
我在脸盆里留了剃须刀和肥皂
I've left a razor and soap on the basin.
去大街上随便找个人  听听他的观点
Listen to the opinions of your man in the street.
他们在政治上  或是别的什么问题上
They're perfectly entitled to give an opinion
都有自己的一套观点
on politics or whatever questions-
但他们没有资格来评论
They've got no qualifications!
他们当然可以评论
Of course they have!
斯宾塞先生有问题要问你
Mr. Spencer would like a word with you.
好心人  我有个问题问你
My good man, I have a question for you.
你是否认为美国的债务形势
Do you suppose the debt situation regarding America
是现在国际贸易减少的主要原因吗
factors significantly in the present low levels of trade?
或者这只是一个假象
Or is this a red herring
弃用金本位制才是最根本的原因
and the abandonment of the gold standard is the cause of the problem?
抱歉  先生  我对您的问题无从回答
I'm sorry, sir, but I am unable to be of assistance in this matter.
哦  太遗憾了
Oh, dear. What a pity.
也许你可以回答我另一个问题
Perhaps you'd help us on another matter.
你是否认为
Do you think
欧洲的货币政策会因为法国和布尔什维克
Europe's currency problem would be alleviated by an arms agreement
的大革命协定而缓和呢
between the French and the Bolsheviks?
抱歉  先生  我对您的问题无从回答
I'm sorry, sir, but I'm unable to be of assistance in this matter.
史蒂文斯  你下去吧
Very well, that'll be all.
等一下  达林顿
One moment, Darlington,
我还有个问题要问这个好心人
I have another question to put to our good man here.
好心人
My good fellow
你是否认同我们的观点
do you share our opinion
达拉第(法国总理)最近在北非的演说
that M. Daladier's recent speech on North Africa
其实是一个诡计
was simply a ruse
用来破坏他们国内的人民阵线
to scupper the nationalist fringe of his own domestic party?
抱歉  先生  我对您的这些问题都无从回答
I'm sorry, sir. I am unable to help in any of these matters.
你们看  他无法回答这些问题
You see, our good man here is " unable to assist us in these matters. "
但是我们要知道一点
Yet we still go along with the notion
民主使得我们国家的决策都由
that this nation's decisions be left to our good man here
像他这样成千上万的大众所决定
and a few millions like him.
就好像让妇联去组织一场战役一样
You may as well ask the Mothers' Union to organize a war campaign.
谢谢  老爷  谢谢  先生
Thank you. Thank you, sir.
您最终证明了你的观点
You certainly proved your point.
-证明终了  -不  你没有证明
-Q.E.D., I think. -No, not at all!
他已经证明了
Oh, yes, he has!
您怎么看镇上的人  都是不错的家伙
What did you make of the citizens of Moscombe? Not a bad bunch.
是的  先生
No, sir.
泰勒夫妇非常好心
Mr. and Mrs. Taylor were extremely kind.
请原谅我的无礼
I say, I hope you don't think me very rude
您的工作是不是男仆之类的
but you aren't a manservant of some sort, are you?
是的  您说对了
Yes, sir. I am, indeed.
事实上  我是达林顿府的管家  在牛津郡附近
In fact, I'm the butler of Darlington Hall, near Oxford.
我并不想刻意隐瞒什么
It wasn't my intention to deceive anyone.
不用解释  我大致能够理解
Don't explain. I can see how it happened.
达林顿
Darlington.
是不是那个达林顿公爵
Wasn't there a Lord Darlington involved
推行的姑息政策让我们卷进了战争
in that appeasement business that got us into the war?
抱歉  我不认识那个达林顿公爵
Sorry, I never knew that Lord Darlington.
我的雇主是一个美国人  刘易斯先生
My employer's an American gentleman, Mr. Lewis.
达林顿公爵是那些想和希特勒谈条件的人之一
Lord Darlington was among those who tried to make a deal with Hitler.
战后好像还有一场官司
Then there was a case after the war
他起诉一家报纸诽谤
where he sued a newspaper for libel.
新闻快报还是新闻时编来着
The Express, was it? News Chronicle?
-我不知道  先生  -不管怎样  他败诉了
-I couldn't say, sir. -Anyway, he lost.
他很幸运  没有以叛国罪论处
He was lucky, really, not to have been tried for treason.
就在那儿  前面
There it is, just ahead.
先生  我要坦白一件事
Sir, I must confess
我没有说真话
that I failed to tell you the truth.
我认识达林顿公爵
I did know Lord Darlington,
我也要说他是一个很正直的好人
and I can declare that he was a truly good man.
完完全全的一个绅士
A gentleman through and through
我为他工作了许多年
to whom I'm proud to have given my best years of service.
这些应该够你到下一个加油站了
That should get you to the next petrol station.
非常感谢  先生
Thank you very much, sir. I'm most grateful.
那你赞同
But did you
他的观点吗
share his opinions?
谁
Who?
达林顿公爵
Lord Darlington.
我是他的管家  我的工作是为他服务
I was his butler. I was there to serve him
无权表示赞同和否定
not to agree or disagree.
你信任他
You trusted him.
是的  非常信任
Yes, I did. Completely.
他在生命的最后几年
But at the end of his life,
他也承认了自己的过错
he himself admitted that he'd been  mistaken.
他太易受人误导  还让自己陷了进去
That he'd been too gullible, and he'd let himself be taken in.
我明白了
I see.
谢谢  先生  您真是太好了
Thank you, sir. You've been most kind.
笔直往前  第一个路口往左
Just keep going straight up here, and turn left at the first crossroads.
我不想烦到您  但是我很好奇
I say, I don't want to be a bore, but I'm intrigued.
您自己持什么立场
Where do you stand on all that?
如果错误在所难免  那您自己犯过什么错吗
If a mistake was to be made, wouldn't you rather have made your own?
抱歉我这么好奇地问您
Forgive me for being so inquisitive.
没关系  先生
Not at all, sir.
某种程度上  我也犯过错
In a very small way, I did make my own mistake.
但是我可能有机会来弥补
But I might have a chance to set mine right.
事实上  我现在正在去弥补的路上
In fact, I'm on my way to try and do so now.
试试看发动
Try the ignition.
谢谢先生  很感谢您的帮助
Thank you, sir. I'm most grateful for your help.
祝好运  很高兴能和您谈话
Good luck. It's been interesting talking to you.
早上好
Good morning.
哈菲克斯公爵很满意那些银制品
Lord Halifax was impressed with the silver.
我告诉他都是你做的  向你献上他的赞美
I told him it was all your doing. Sent his compliments. Well done.
史蒂文斯  我想问你
I've been meaning to ask you
去年那两个犹太女仆的事
That business last year about the Jewish maids
是不是已经找不到她们了
I suppose there's no way of tracing them?
估计很难  我曾试过在萨里郡帮她们找份工
That would be difficult. I tried to get them a position in Surrey.
但那里只有一个空缺  她们又不想被分开
There was room only for one, and they didn't want to be separated.
好吧  你再试试吧  得为她们做点什么
Well, try anyway. One would like to do something for them.
解雇她们是错误的决定
It was wrong, what occurred.
我对此很自责
I'm sorry about it. Very sorry.
-早上好  -早上好
-Good morning. -Good morning.
老爷问起那两个犹太女仆
He asked about the Jewish girls.
-艾尔莎和厄尔玛  -他想知道她们在哪
-Elsa and Irma? -He wondered where they were.
他说解雇她们是错误的决定
He said it was wrong to dismiss them.
我记得您当初跟我一样感到沮丧
I remember you were as distressed as I was about it.
跟您一样
As you were?
您不是认为她们应该被赶走吗
You thought it was right and proper that they should be sent packing.
您这么说我真是太不公平了
Now, really, that is most unfair.
那时我也很不安  非常不安
Of course I was upset. Very much so.
我从不希望发生这样的事
I don't like that happening here.
我真希望您那时能告诉我
I wish you'd told me.
这样我就会好受多了
It would've helped me to know you felt as I did.
你为什么总是把自己的感情藏的很深
Why do you always have to hide what you feel?
薰衣草袋都弄好了吗  很好
Have you finished the lavender bags? Good.
我向您承认
I take my hat off to you.
这女孩确实做的不错  您是对的
That girl's come along very well. You were right and I was wrong.
-看看你脸上的笑容  -什么笑容
-Look at that smile on your face. -What smile?
这笑容不言而喻
That tells a story in itself.
您不这样想吗  史蒂文斯先生
Wouldn't you say so?
什么意思
What story's that?
她长的很漂亮  不是吗
She's a pretty girl, don't you think?
是吗
Is she?
我注意到您不雇佣漂亮女孩子
You don't like pretty girls on the staff. I've noticed.
看来是我们的史蒂文斯先生担心因此分神
Might it be that our Mr. Stevens fears distraction?
是不是因为史蒂文斯先生也是血肉之躯
Can it be that Mr. Stevens is flesh and blood
怕自己控制不住呢
and cannot trust himself?
你知道我此刻在做什么吗
You know what I'm doing?
你在唠唠叨叨的时候  我在神游
I'm placing my thoughts elsewhere while you chatter away.
为什么那种有罪似的笑容还在您脸上
Why is that guilty smile still on your face?
只是因为你的唠叨而感到好笑而已
Not guilty, simply amused by the nonsense you sometimes talk.
绝对是被我说中了  你无法正眼看她
It is a guilty smile. You can't bear to look at her.
所以你不想雇她  因为她太漂亮了
You didn't want her. She was too pretty.
算你说对了
You must be right.
你总是对的
You always are.
查理
Charlie!
丽兹  你不是应该在整理床铺吗
Lizzie, aren't you supposed to be turning down the beds?
那你最好快点
Well, you better get on with it, then.
你还没告诉她吗  那你得快点告诉她
Have you told her yet? You better get on with it, then.
我该怎么跟她说  她不会懂的
What can I say to her? She'd never understand.
-为什么  -她已经老了  至少30多岁
-Why not? -She's old. She must be at least 30.
也许她不觉得自己老呢
Perhaps she doesn't feel old.
你觉得她经常摘的那些花是给谁的
Who do you think those flowers are for she's been picking?
过来  给我个吻
Come here. Give us a kiss.
花儿
Flowers.
你在看书
You're reading.
这里很暗  你看得见吗
It's very dim. Can you see?
是的  谢谢关心
Yes, thank you.
你在读什么
What are you reading?
一本书
A book.
我知道  什么样的书
Yes, but what sort of book?
就是一本书  肯顿小姐
It's a book, Miss Kenton. A book.
什么书
What's the book?
你难道对自己看的书感到羞愧
Are you shy about your book?
让我看看
What is it?
色情书
Is it racy?
Racy?
你在看一本色情书吗
Are you reading a racy book?
你觉得老爷的书房里会有色情书吗
Do you think racy books are to be found in His Lordship's shelves?
我怎么知道
How would I know?
是什么书
What is it?
让我看看  让我看看你的书
Let me see it. Let me see your book.
请让我一个人待着
Please leave me alone.
为什么不让我看看你的书
Why won't you show me your book?
现在是我的私人时间  您这是在干扰我
This is my private time. You're invading it.
是这样吗
Is that so?
我在干扰您的私人时间  是吗
I'm invading your private time, am I?
书里有什么
What's in that book?
让我看看
Come on, let me see.
还是说你在保护我
Or are you protecting me? Is that what you're doing?
怕我被震惊到吗
Would I be shocked?
会给我带来心理阴影吗
Would it ruin my character?
让我看看
Let me see it.
哦  天哪
Oh, dear.
这书一点也不会让人感到羞耻
It's not scandalous at all.
这只是一本多愁善感的爱情小说
It's just a sentimental old love story.
我读这些书
I read these books
还有其他的书
any books
是为了提高我的英语知识水平
to develop my command and knowledge of the English language.
我读书是为了见多识广  肯顿小姐
I read to further my education, Miss Kenton.
我真心地请求您
I really must ask you, please
请不要打扰我为数不多的属于自己的时间
not to disturb the few moments I have to myself.
请进
Come in.
什么事
What is it?
我想辞职
I'm wanting to give you my notice, please.
为什么
Why?
查理和我准备结婚
Charlie and me, we're getting married.
你仔细考虑过了没
Have you thought about this carefully?
是的  肯顿小姐
Yes, Miss Kenton, I have.
你在这里越做越好  而且有大好的前途
You've been getting on well here and could have a fine career before you.
查理和吾准备结婚
Charlie and me's getting married.
查理和我
Charlie and I.
但愿我知道该怎么对你说
I wish I knew what to say to you.
我见过这样的事很多次了
I've seen this happen so many times.
年轻的女士急于结婚  最后落得失望的结局
A young girl rushing into marriage only to be disappointed in the end.
你们有钱吗
What about money?
我们没有钱
We don't have any.
只要有爱就行
But who cares?
你们慢慢会知道过穷日子是很艰难的
You'll find it's not easy to live poor.
但我们有彼此
We have each other.
人生路上不就图一个知心伴侣嘛
That's all anyone can ever need.
很好
Very well.
如果你确定的话
If you're so sure.
谢谢
Thank you.
祝好运
Good luck.
我们尽力了
We did all we could for them.
我告诉他
I told him
他将是一个有潜质的副管家
I had my eye on him as a possible under-butler
再过个一两年
in a year or so.
但是他自己的事自己决定
But, no, Mr. Charlie knows best.
她肯定会失望的
She's sure to be let down.
现在说这些也是无济于事了
No use crying over spilt milk.
况且  我们还有其他重要的事要讨论
Besides, we have far more important matters to discuss.
-下周的会议   -我们非得今晚谈论吗
-Next week's meeting. Now--Must we discuss it tonight?
什么
Sorry?
我很累了
I'm tired.
您看不出来  我今天忙了一整天吗
I've had a busy day. Don't you realize that?
我非常累
I'm very tired.
我非常  非常累了
I'm very, very tired.
你不明白吗
Don't you understand?
我要跟您道歉  我以为
I owe you an apology. I thought
定期在夜间讨论有助于我们白天的工作
these quiet evening talks were useful to our work.
现在看来  对您是一种负担
But now I see that they're a burden to you.
我只是说今晚很累了
I was only saying I was tired tonight.
不  您是对的
No, no. You're right.
我们的讨论在一整天之后是一种体力的负担
Our meetings are a burden after a long day.
我们最好还是取消了吧
Perhaps we'd better discontinue them.
讨论很有用  只是今天我太累了
They're useful. It was only tonight.
感谢您泡的热可可
I thank you for the cocoa.
以后我们在白天讨论吧
In the future, we shall communicate only during the day.
如果可以的话  就用写字条的方式
If necessary, by written message.
祝您晚安
I wish you a very good night.
我明天要请个假
I shall be taking my day off tomorrow.
9点30分之前我会回来的
I'll be back in the house by 9:30.
可以
Certainly.
当然
晚安
Good night.
我很高兴能够从庄园出来  我可以告诉你
I'm glad to be out of it, I can tell you.
杰弗瑞爵士和他的黑衫党
There was something about Sir Geoffrey and his Black Shirts
让我心惊胆战的
gave me the creeps.
史蒂文斯先生总说管理庄园
Mr. Stevens says we should run the house
要把自己的私人事务放在一边
and leave the rest where it belongs.
你不同意吧  贝恩先生
You don't agree, Mr. Benn.
我也是
Nor do I, really.
如果我要表示不喜欢
If I don't like something,
我就会说  够了  别说了
I want to say stuff it
请你原谅我的用词  肯顿小姐
if you'll pardon the expression, Miss Kenton.
看来我做管家不像史蒂文斯先生那么专业
But then I suppose I'm not a real professional, like Mr. Stevens.
史蒂文斯先生的一生都是管家
It's Mr. Stevens' whole life.
但我不一样
Well, it's not mine.
告诉你件事情
And to tell you the truth
我不准备回去服侍雇主了
I don't want to go back in service.
-那你要做什么  贝恩先生  -叫我汤姆
-What would you do instead, Mr. Benn? -Tom's the name.
汤姆
Tom.
那你准备找份什么样的工作
What employment would you take up?
我准备自己开始做生意
I'd really like to be on my own.
开家小店  卖报纸和香烟
Start a little shop somewhere, newspapers and tobacco.
或者去西南部的老家开家小旅店
Or a boarding house in the west country, where I come from.
克利夫顿很适合开小旅店  就在海边
Clevedon's a good place for a boarding house.
再喝一点吧
Would I get you another shandy?
已经9点30分了
Well, it's almost 9:30
拜托
Go on!
今天不是放假嘛
It's your day off, isn't it?
你又不是在军队  要踩时点回去
You're not in the army, due back in the barracks.
-好吧  再来一杯  -很好
-All right, then. -Good.
请再给我半杯
Half a shandy, please.
那你呢  莎拉
What about yourself, then, Sarah?
这个名字太一本正经
That's a serious sort of a name.
我母亲在世的时候  大家称呼我莎莉
They called me Sally when my mum was alive.
莎莉  很美
Sally. That's nice.
你想一辈子做女管家吗
Is it your intention to remain in service?
这是一个很好的职业  至少有份工作
It's a good profession, when you have a position.
史蒂文斯先生说我们很幸运
Mr. Stevens says we're fortunate
我们不是在谈论他
We're not talking about him.
我们是在谈论你
We're talking about you.
假设
Supposing
有人邀请你去做海边的小旅馆的女主人
someone asked if you'd like to come in on a boarding house by the sea?
你怎么想
What would you say?
我不知道
Well, I don't know.
这是个假想的问题  所以我不会去想
It's a theoretical question, so I haven't given it any thought
-贝恩先生  -叫我汤姆
-  Mr. Benn. -Tom.
如果这不是个假想的问题
Supposing it wasn't theoretical
莎莉
Sally?
已经很久没人叫我这个名字了  感觉很滑稽
It's been years since I've been called that. It feels funny.
但感觉很好吧
Nice, though?
很晚了
It's very late.
还有别的事吗  老爷
Will there be anything else?
什么
What?
-谢谢  晚安  -晚安  老爷
-Thank you. Good night. -Good night, my lord.
卡迪纳尔先生  晚上好
Mr. Cardinal, good evening.
-你好吗  -很好
-How are you? -Very well.
-很好  那你妻子呢  -也很好  先生
-Delighted. And your wife? -Very well too, sir.
-你好吗  -很好  先生
-How are you? -Very well, sir.
今天我的安排计划有点混乱
I've gone and got myself in a bit of a mess with arrangements.
公爵能让我在这里待一晚吗
Would His Lordship put me up?
我会告诉他您来了
I'll tell him you're here.
但愿今天没有什么特殊的事情
I hope there's nothing special tonight.
老爷在晚饭后有几个客人要见
His Lordship expects some gentlemen after dinner.
那我尽量低调  反正我也要专心写我的专栏
I'll keep my head down, then. I've got to write my column anyway.
-您正好赶上晚餐时间  -但愿不麻烦你
-You're in time for dinner, if you like. -I hoped I would be.
我的教父他怎么样  身体好吗
How is my godfather? Fit?
很好  您要点心吗
Very well. Some refreshment?
谢谢  再来点威士忌就更好了
Thank you. Some whisky would be lovely.
-他今晚要见谁   -我也没法回答您
-Who's he expecting tonight? -I am unable to help you there.
什么  你也不知道
What, no idea?
一点也不知道  先生
No idea at all, sir.
-那我会很低调的  -你做的对  先生
-I'll keep my head down all the same. -I think it's a good idea, sir.
请进
Come in.
卡迪纳尔先生刚到  让人出乎意料
Mr. Cardinal has just arrived, out of the blue.
给他准备一下他的房间
He'll expect his usual room.
-我出门前会去确认的  -你要出去
-I'll see to it before I leave. -You're going out?
是的
I am indeed.
今天是星期四
It's Thursday.
哦  我忘记了  抱歉
Of course. I'd forgotten. Sorry.
有什么事情
Is something the matter?
有些客人要来  但跟您没什么关系
Some visitors are arriving, but it doesn't involve you.
虽然每周四我都可以放假
We agreed that Thursday is my day off
但如果你急需我帮忙
but if you need me urgently-
不用  今晚没什么事  谢谢
No, it's perfectly all right. Thank you.
我有事要告诉你
I have something to tell you.
我的朋友
My friend
就是我去见的人  贝恩先生
the man I'm meeting, Mr. Benn.
贝恩先生  我知道
Mr. Benn. Of course. Yes.
他向我求婚了
He has asked me to marry him.
我还在考虑
I am thinking about it.
我明白了
I see.
他下个月要回到西南部去
He's moving to the west country next month.
我也还在考虑
I'm still thinking about it.
我想事先通知您一下
I thought you should be informed of the situation.
好的  谢谢
Yes, thank you.
您真是太好心了
That's most kind of you.
祝您今晚过的愉快
I trust you'll have a most pleasant evening.
今晚什么有什么特别的事吗
Is there something special tonight?
您的访客  他们很特殊吗
Are your visitors special?
不能告诉你  我的孩子  绝对保密
Can't tell you, my boy. Strictly confidential.
-所以我不能在场了咯   -在哪
-So I can't sit in on it? -On what?
-你们会见的地方  -绝对不行
-Whatever it is that's taking place. -Absolutely not.
像你这样的新闻记者不能插足这件事
Can't have someone like you sticking your nose in. A journalist.
你们怎么称来着  "狗仔队"
What do you call it, a " newshound"?
绝对不行
No, it wouldn't do at all.
吃好晚餐  你就别出来了
Once you've had your food, you'd better make yourself scarce.
看来很神秘的样子
It sounds pretty special to me.
晚上好  首相
Good evening, prime minister.
-抱歉  我们被耽搁了  -我能理解
-Sorry, we've been delayed. -I understand.
哈菲克斯公爵
Lord Halifax.
-很高兴见到您  -这是弗雷泽先生
-Very nice to see you. -This is Mr. Fraser.
晚上好  阁下
Good evening, Your Excellency.
请稍等  阁下  我去告知公爵
Please wait here, Your Excellency. I'll inform His Lordship.
我们不想把大英帝国卷入战争
We don't intend to involve the whole British Empire in a war
仅仅因为在远方的一个小国家发生的争端
simply because of a quarrel in a faraway country
那里的人我们还完全不了解
between people of whom we know nothing.
对我来说  整个捷克斯洛伐克民族
To my mind, the whole of Czechoslovakia
还不如我们国家的任何一个年轻人
isn't worth a single one of our own young men.
我们这里一群小国家吵嚷着要战争
We have a small, noisy and corrupt war group here
却没有意识到你们德国只是在清理自己的后院
who don't realize that you Germans are marching into your own back yard.
元首打心底里是一个和平主义者
The Fhrer is a man of peace to the depth of his soul
但他绝不允许一个二流国家
but he won't allow a small second-rate country
在德意志帝国1000年的历史中指着自己的鼻子
to thumb its nose at the 1000-year German Reich.
我去吧
I'll get it.
快醒醒
Come on, wake up!
保持清醒
Stay awake!
您能认出这位小姐是这儿的职员吗
Could you confirm that this lady is on the staff here?
是的  她是这儿的女管家
Yes, of course. She's the housekeeper.
谢谢  先生
Thank you, sir.
-我可以走了吗  -当然  小姐
-May I? -Of course.
抱歉把您当坏人了
Sorry to have alarmed you.
只是以防万一
Just security, miss.
我相信您肯定过了一个很愉快的夜晚
I trust you've had a pleasant evening.
您过得愉快吗
Well, did you have a pleasant evening?
-是的  谢谢  -很好
-Yes, thank you. -Good.
你不想知道发生什么事吗
Would you like to know what took place?
我必须上楼去了
I have to return upstairs.
今晚有重要的事情
There are important events taking place tonight.
什么时候不是呢
When are there not?
我接受了
I accepted his proposal.
我接受了贝恩先生的求婚
I accepted Mr. Benn's proposal of marriage.
恭喜您
My congratulations.
我准备交出辞职信了
I am prepared to serve out my notice.
如果您能早点放我走  我将感激不尽
But if you'd release me earlier, I'd be grateful.
贝恩先生打算半个月内就动身
Mr. Benn is planning to leave for the west country in two weeks.
我尽力
I'll do my best.
请恕我失陪
Now, please excuse me.
我在这儿工作了这么多年  你没什么要说吗
After all the years I have been here, you have nothing else to say?
我向您献上最诚挚的祝福
You have my warmest congratulations.
您是一个非常重要的人
You've been a very important figure
对于我和贝恩先生
for Mr. Benn and me.
怎么重要
Oh, in what way?
我告诉他所有您的细节
I tell him all sorts of things about you.
我告诉他您的故事  您的习惯
I tell him stories about you. About your habits.
关于您的言谈举止
About your mannerisms.
他觉得十分有趣  特别是您
He finds it very funny, especially when I show him how
往食物上洒胡椒粉的时候会捏住鼻子
you pinch your nose when you put pepper on your food.
这总让我们忍不住大笑
That always has us in stitches.
是吗
Does it, indeed?
那么  请
Well, please
允许我失陪  肯顿小姐
excuse me, Miss Kenton.
晚安
Good night.
谢谢
Thanks.
我们做了很长时间的朋友  是吧
We've been friends a long time, haven't we?
我每次来这儿  总是期待跟你谈话
I always look forward to a chat when I come here.
你可以跟我坐下来一起喝一杯吗
Would you care to join me in a drink?
您真好  但是不了  谢谢
That's most kind of you, but no, thank you.
你没事吧
You all right?
我非常好
I'm perfectly all right.
没有觉得不舒服吗
Not feeling unwell, are you?
只是有点累
A little tired, perhaps.
肯定的  现在都  凌晨1点了
I bet you're tired. What is it, about 1:00?
过来
Come on.
我要你坐下
I want you to sit down.
先生  我真的
Well, sir, I really-
我不是碰巧才来这儿的
I didn't come here by accident.
你知道吧
You know that.
我有条线报  关于
I had a tip-off, you see
现在正在书房里的客人
about what's going on now in the library.
我希望你坐下  我是你的朋友
I wish you'd sit down. I'm your friend
你总端着盘子  好像随时就要走似的
and you're holding that tray as if you're about to wander off!
过来  坐下
Now, come on. Sit down, damn it!
好多了
That's better.
听着  我猜首相不在书房里吧
Now, look, I don't suppose the prime minister is in the library, is he?
首相  先生
Prime minister, sir?
在书房  你不用做什么确认
In the library-You don't have to confirm it-
我们的首相  外交大臣  德国大使
-are our prime minister, our foreign secretary and the German ambassador.
-你猜他们在谈些什么  -我不知道
-Any idea what they're talking about? -I'm afraid not.
告诉我  史蒂文斯  你一点也不关心吗
Tell me, Stevens, don't you care at all?
你一点也不感到好奇吗
Aren't you in the least bit curious?
我无权对这些事情感兴趣
It's not my place to be curious about such matters.
你无权
Not your place.
假设我告诉你  公爵
And supposing I told you that His Lordship
正在试图说服首相
is trying to persuade the prime minister
跟柏林那些战争犯达成协议
to enter into a pact with that bunch of criminals in Berlin?
我深信老爷肯定有他最高尚的出发点
I'm certain His Lordship is acting from the highest and noblest motives.
你不明白吗  就是这一点让人感到讨厌
Don't you see? That's exactly what makes it so abominable!
把这些崇高的好意扭曲成了糟糕的结局
Twisting these high and noble motives to their own foul ends!
请你务必要意识到  公爵正在成为
You do, please, realize that His Lordship's been the most
纳粹在我们国家最有价值的棋子
valuable pawn that the Nazis have in this country
只是因为他把别人想的太好了
precisely because he is good and honourable?
要我没有喝太多酒  就能让你明白了
If I weren't so drunk, I could make you understand!
先生
Sir
我明白的
I do understand.
老爷正在努力维持我们时代的和平
His Lordship is working to ensure peace in our time.
建立在他们猛兽般的条款上的和平
Peace in our time on their beastly terms!
记得那次会议上的美国人吗
Remember that American here at the conference?
把达林顿公爵称为业余者
Called Lord Darlington an amateur, out of his depth?
他倒是说对了
Well, he was right.
他说的太对了
He was dead right.
我真不知道该怎么跟你谈论公爵
I hardly have to tell you how I feel towards His Lordship.
我跟你一样都非常地关心他
I care about him deeply, and I know you do too.
是的
Yes, I do indeed.
那你怎能忍心看他犯下如此严重的错误
Then aren't you desperate to see him make this mistake?
他被玩弄了  你不明白吗
He's being tricked! Don't you see?
还是你跟他一样被蒙蔽了双眼
Or are you as deluded as he is?
天哪  我可能真的冒犯到你了
Oh, dear. Now I've probably offended you.
没关系  先生
No. Not at all, sir.
没关系
Not at all.
请原谅我失陪
You must excuse me.
还有其他客人需要我
There are other gentlemen calling for me, sir.
请不要在意我说的话
You mustn't take anything I said to heart.
我刚才太失礼了
I was very foolish a little while ago.
我没有太当真
I haven't taken anything you said to heart.
实际上  我都不记得了
In fact, I can hardly recall anything you did say.
我只是太傻了
I was just being very foolish.
我实在没有时间跟您站在这儿闲谈
I simply haven't time to stand here with you, engaging in idle talk.
建议您上床睡觉  您一定很累了
I suggest you go to bed now. You must be very tired.
晚安
Good night.
我想告诉您
I'd been wanting to tell you
早餐室外面有个角落
It's the small alcove outside the breakfast room.
可能是新来的女仆不熟悉
It's the new girl, of course
我看到好几次都有积灰尘
but I find it has not been dusted in some time.
我会去看看的
I'll see to it.
谢谢
Thank you.
我知道您会想要知道的
I knew you would have wanted to be informed.
你好  莎莉
Hello, Sally.
嗨  汤姆
Hi, Tom.
你没事吧
You all right, then?
你呢
How are you?
我很好
I'm good.
我们可以稍谈一会吗  就一会
Could we talk for a moment, please? Just for a moment.
最好快点  我正好要出去
We'll have to be quick because I'm going out.
不会很久的
It won't take long.
好吧  我们去客厅谈
All right, then. We'll have to go into the lounge.
下午好
Afternoon.
舒适的小房间  不错
Nice little place, isn't it?
有点像我们想象中的小旅馆
The sort of quiet little boarding house I had in mind for us.
像其他事情一样  也没能做成
Like other things, it didn't work out.
你有什么事要说
What did you want to say?
我昨天见到凯瑟琳  她有些好消息
I saw Catherine yesterday. She had some interesting news.
她怀孕了
She's expecting.
哦  天哪
Oh, my goodness!
她想让我们礼拜天去喝杯茶
She wants us both over for tea on Sunday.
我可以来接你
I could come and get you.
我们可以一起坐巴士去
We could go together on the bus.
我再考虑一下
Yes, well, we'll see about that.
没有了你  房子都是空荡荡的
House is that empty without you.
我没法告诉你
I can't tell you.
你又在刮胡须的时候划伤了
You cut yourself shaving.
我知道
Oh, yeah. I know.
这些天  做什么都不对劲
Can't seem to do anything right these days.
史蒂文斯  我经常想起那些美好时光
I so often think of the good old days
那时我曾是达林顿府女管家
when I was housekeeper at Darlington Hall.
那些年是我一生中最快乐的时光
Those years with you were the happiest of my life.
您还要再来点茶吗
Would you like more tea?
是的  谢谢
Yes, please. Thank you.
肯顿小姐  抱歉  贝恩夫人
Miss Kenton. I'm sorry, Mrs. Benn.
-抱歉  我来晚了  -没关系
-Sorry, I was delayed. -That's all right.
请坐
Please sit down.
-我点了一壶茶  -很好
-I've ordered some fresh tea. -Lovely.
您要来点蛋糕吗
Would you like some cake?
-真的不要   -最近发胖了
-Sure? -All right. It's a special occasion.
好吧
Good.
服务生
Waitress?
-请给我来一份蛋糕  -好的
-Could we have some cake? -Yes, of course.
-多年不见啊  -是啊
-It's been a long time. -Yes, indeed.
您一点也没变
You haven't changed at all.
也许  一点点
A little, perhaps.
我们都有变化
We've all changed, I think.
无论到哪我都会认得你
I'd have known you anywhere.
多久了没见了  20年了吧
How long's it been? Twenty years?
我想正好刚过20年
Yes, just over, I think.
茶怎么还没来
The tea should be along.
我们从报纸上看到了诽谤案
We read about the suit for libel.
这是个耻辱
It's a shame
竟然称达林顿公爵为叛国者
calling His Lordship a traitor.
报纸真是什么都敢写
Those papers will print anything.
他们不该赢这个案子的
They should have lost the case.
当老爷走上法庭的时候
When His Lordship went to court
他真诚地希望自己能得到公正
he sincerely expected he would get justice.
然而  报社还变本加厉
Instead, the newspaper increased its circulation, and His Lordship's
老爷的好名声全给毁了
good name was destroyed forever.
之后  在他生命的最后几年
Afterwards, in his last years, well
老实说  贝恩夫人
quite honestly, Mrs. Benn
他已经心碎了
his heart was broken.
我送茶到书房  而他只是坐在那里
I'd take him tea in the library, and he'd be sitting there
他看也不看我  沉浸在他自己的世界里
and he wouldn't even see me, so deep was he in his own thoughts.
他还会自言自语  就像在跟别人争论什么似的
And he'd be talking to himself, as though he was arguing with someone.
当然  只有他一个人
There was no one, of course.
不再有人来看他了
No one came to see him anymore.
那他的教子  卡迪纳尔先生呢
What about his godson, young Mr. Cardinal?
卡迪纳尔先生在战争中牺牲了
Mr. Cardinal was killed in the war. Waitress.
我要结帐
May I have my bill, please?
我很抱歉听到这个消息
I'm very sorry.
我知道您脑海中的达林顿府是它最繁盛的时期
I know you remember Darlington Hall in its best days
老爷也希望这样被铭记
and that's how His Lordship deserves to be remembered.
可能这些好时光会再来  因为刘易斯先生来了
But perhaps the good days are back, now that Mr. Lewis is here
刘易斯太太也将到来
and Mrs. Lewis is arriving shortly.
他们很幸运  能有你管理房子
Very fortunate to have you running the house.
我们还是有点问题  肯顿小姐  抱歉  贝恩夫人
We still have problems, Miss Kenton. I'm sorry. Mrs. Benn.
-我们还是有点人手问题  -你在信里有提到
-We still have staff problems. -You mentioned it in your letter.
老实说  我也在想回去做女管家
Frankly, I've been thinking of going back in service.
很好
Good-
但是现在情形变了
But now the situation has changed for me.
如果我要找份工作  我将
If I take up any work, it will have to be
找一份在这儿的工作
here in the west country
因为凯瑟琳  我女儿怀孕了
because Catherine, our daughter, is expecting a baby.
我想待在她身边
So I would like to be near her.
当然
Of course.
然后待在孙子的身边  陪他长大
And to be near our grandchild as he grows up.
-这是自然的  -或者孙女  如果是个女孩的话
-Naturally. -Or her, if it's a little girl.
多年前我离开达林顿府的时候
When I left Darlington Hall, all those years ago
我并没有意识到是真的离开了
I never realized I was really, truly leaving.
我总想着离开那儿是为了
I believe I thought of it as simply another ruse
让你烦恼
to annoy you.
突然意识到自己已婚  让我很是惊讶
It was a shock to come out here and find myself actually married.
很长一段时间  我都
For a long time, I was
很不幸福
very unhappy.
后来凯瑟琳出生了  一年一年过去
But then Catherine was born, the years went by and one day
然后意识到我爱我的丈夫
I realized I loved my husband.
知道吗  这世界上
You see, there is no one
没有人会像他那般地需要我
no one in the world who needs me as much as he does.
但时不时地
But still there are times
我也会觉得曾犯了一个天大的错误
when I think I made a terrible mistake with my life.
我想我们都会有这样的想法
I'm sure we all have these thoughts
时不时地
from time to time.
人们总是在夜晚亮灯时欢呼
People always cheer when they turn the lights on in the evening.
我想知道为什么
I wonder why.
人们常说
They do say
对许多人来说  夜晚是一天中最好的时光
that for many people, the evening's the best part of the day.
是他们最期待的时刻
The part they most look forward to.
是吗
Is that so?
您最期待的是什么  史蒂文斯
What do you most look forward to?
首要的是  回到达林顿府
Getting back to Darlington Hall, principally
把人手问题解决掉
and straightening out our staff problems.
您对这些事总是很在行
You were always able to do that.
我想您肯定有很多事情要处理
And you had quite a few to straighten out, as I remember.
总是在工作  工作  更多的工作
Always was work, work and more work
然后依旧会如此  毫无疑问
and will continue to be so, I have no doubt.
史蒂文斯  不用等在那里  这班巴士总是晚点
Mr. Stevens, don't you wait! That bus is always late.
过来躲躲雨吧
Come in out of the wet.
你要好好照顾自己
You must take good care of yourself.
-你也是  向我保证  -是的  向你保证
-You too, promise me that. -Oh, yes, I promise.
尽可能地让你和你丈夫幸福吧
Do all you can to make these years happy for yourself and your husband.
我们可能再也见不到面了  贝恩夫人
We may never meet again, Mrs. Benn.
所以我以个人名义说  请原谅我
That is why I am being personal, if you will forgive me.
谢谢  史蒂文斯
Thank you, Mr. Stevens.
车来了  偏偏今天准点了
Oh, here it comes. It's on time for once.
谢谢  谢谢你能来
Thank you. And thank you so very much for coming.
你真是太好了
It was so very kind of you.
非常高兴能再见到你
It was so nice to see you.
我也很高兴能再见到你  再见
It was a pleasure to see you again. Goodbye.
当心
Take care.
你吓到我了  你从哪儿蹦出来的
You scared me. Where'd you come from?
你喜欢这件吗
You like the suit?
很好  先生
Very good, sir.
很好
Good.
当心上面的吊灯
Watch the chandelier there.
你真是安排的井井有条  太好了
You're really getting things going here. This is wonderful!
我不得不叫上镇上的三个姑娘来帮忙
I've had to ask another three girls from the village to come up.
我向您保证刘易斯夫人来之前
And I can promise you that the house will be ready
一切都会如期准备妥当
and in shape by the time Mrs. Lewis arrives.
好极了
That sounds good.
下午我要见一个女管家应聘者
I'm expecting a possible new housekeeper this afternoon.
露丝?马斯普拉特夫人
A Mrs. Ruth Muspratt.
有很好的推荐信  她在苏塞克斯做过学校督导
Excellent references. She was matron at a boys' school in Sussex.
督导
A matron?
听上去好像她会好好监督言行举止
Sounds like she'll keep us from misbehaving.
-但愿  先生  -好吧
-I certainly hope so, sir. -Good.
很好  史蒂文斯  非常好
Good, Stevens. Very good.
这里是35年会议的那个宴会厅  记得吗
This is where we had that banquet back in '35. Remember?
我们都站起来  发表自己的观点
We all stood up and delivered ourselves of our principles.
天知道我说了什么  不知道有没有起作用
God knows what I said. Sure got worked up about it, though.
我到底说了什么  史蒂文斯
What did I say, anyway?
抱歉  先生  我那时忙着做事
I'm sorry, sir, I was too busy serving
没时间听你们的演说
to listen to the speeches.
我们有个访客来了
We got a visitor here.
当心
Be very careful.
过来  小家伙  过来
Come here. That's a boy. Come on.
慢慢来
Okay. Easy does it.
过来
Come on!
不要去吓它
You don't want to startle it.
它会下来的
It'll come down.
我们把窗打开
I think if we leave the window open
很好
Good.
差一点
Very still.
去吧  出去吧
Go on. Out! Come on. Out!
做的好
Well done.
做的好  先生
Well done, sir.